<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The gospel-call in metre compiled by W.V. ; whereunto is added twenty five considerations of the pains prepared for sin  after this life, with a sermon preached on Acts VII. 60.</title>
            <author>W. V.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95838</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V14A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42509</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36282178</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36282178</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150340</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95838)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150340)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2242:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The gospel-call in metre compiled by W.V. ; whereunto is added twenty five considerations of the pains prepared for sin  after this life, with a sermon preached on Acts VII. 60.</title>
                  <author>W. V.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 126, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Butler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Twenty five considerations of the pains prepared for sin after this life ..." has special t.p. and continuous paging.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts VII, 60 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150340:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE GOSPEL-CALL.</p>
                  <p>In METRE.</p>
                  <p>Compiled by <hi>W. V.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whereunto is added Twenty Five Conſiderations OF THE PAINS prepared for SIN After this Life.</p>
                  <p>WITH A SERMON <hi>Preached on</hi> Acts VII. 60.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Bleſſed is the people that know the joyful ſound,</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal. 89.15.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>To day if you will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ear his voice, harden not your hearts,</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſ. 95.7, 8.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>Hear and your ſoul ſhall live,</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Iſa. 55.3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>Riſe, he calleth thee,</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Mark 10.49.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Butler,</hi> in <hi>White-Lion-Court,</hi> in <hi>Barbican.</hi> 1688.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150340:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150340:2"/>
                  <head>THE PUBLISHER TO THE READER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Honeſt Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE ſad Degeneracy of the Age we live in, makes it appear but too great a Truth, That ſuch Books as theſe were never more neceſſary or more ſeaſonable: And therefore I hope there needs no Apology for publiſhing this. The following Papers came recommended to me from Perſons of known Honeſty and Integrity. Our Author has thought fit in Modeſty to conceal his Name, and I will not trouble my ſelf or thee with impertinent Gueſſes: Nor will I pretend poſitively to determine why he has cloath'd part of his Conceptions in a Poetick Dreſs, ſince Examples are not wanting in all times in
<pb facs="tcp:150340:3"/>this kind. The Royal Prophets, <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> have excell'd in Divine Poeſie; And we are not wanting in our own Age of great Men, famous in our Generation, who have oblig'd the World with their Excellent Labours of this Nature; witneſs the Famous <hi>Quarles,</hi> Inimitable <hi>Cowley,</hi> Facetious <hi>Donne,</hi> and the Divine <hi>Herbert</hi> (to name no more), who gives this Excellent Reaſon:</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>A Verſe may find him who a Sermon flies,</l>
                     <l>And turn Delight into a Sacrifice.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>As for the following Diſcourſe, 'tis plain and honeſt, fitted to the meaneſt Capacities, which, I hope, will render it univerſally accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. It treats of things of the greateſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and higheſt Conſequence, no leſs than the Concerns of Eternity. I will no longer detain thee from the Peruſal, which, I wiſh, may redound to thy great benefit. I heartily recommend it to thee, and thee to the Grace of God. I am</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Thine,</hi> R. B,</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150340:3"/>
                  <head>To the Author of the <hi>Goſpel-Call.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>THY <hi>Goſpel-Call</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Dear Friend) has out-done all</l>
                  <l>Thoſe gaudy florid Strains,</l>
                  <l>Which puzzle Vulgar Brains.</l>
                  <l>Thy Book has Worth,</l>
                  <l>Which needs no ſetting forth</l>
                  <l>By my weak Pen;</l>
                  <l>The Praiſe is thine,</l>
                  <l>For which thy Name ſhall ſhine</l>
                  <l>Bright, like the Morning-Star,</l>
                  <l>Which uſhers in the Day from far,</l>
                  <l>Until the Reſtitution of all things agen.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>T. D.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150340:4"/>
                  <head>To the Author of the <hi>Goſpel-Call.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>AWake my Muſe, how can I ſilent be,</l>
                  <l>When I theſe pious Works of <hi>David</hi> ſee?</l>
                  <l>They that peruſe this little Book, may find</l>
                  <l>The wiſe Suggeſtions of the Author's Mind,</l>
                  <l>How wittily this Worthy does impart</l>
                  <l>His Sentiments with Judgment, and with Art,</l>
                  <l>In Stile moſt Elegant, in Sence profound,</l>
                  <l>In Morals practical, and Doctrine ſound.</l>
                  <l>Who, like a <hi>Geographer,</hi> does here diſplay</l>
                  <l>To Heaven the ſureſt, and the ſafeſt way:</l>
                  <l>In Goſpel-Colours does delineate</l>
                  <l>The lively Landſchape of our future State.</l>
                  <l>Dull Soul, chear up, here, here's thy chiefest Good,</l>
                  <l>'Tis not Terreſtrial, but Celeſtial Food.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>A. T.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150340:4"/>
                  <head>THE GOSPEL-CALL.</head>
                  <head type="sub">In METRE.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>READER, awake, awake, my Soul and all</l>
                     <l>That is within me, hearken to the Call</l>
                     <l>Of God, moſt gracious; who calleth thee</l>
                     <l>His Name to hallow and to glorifie;</l>
                     <l>And from vile luſts, vain glory, cheating pelf,</l>
                     <l>Invites thee to Communion with himſelf.</l>
                     <l>This is thy chief end, thy Felicity,</l>
                     <l>Thy greateſt good, thy higheſt dignity.</l>
                     <l>Here is Light, Life, Love, all that's meet,</l>
                     <l>Needful and uſeful, holy, right, and ſweet;</l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:150340:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>And all which truly fills the heart and eyes;</l>
                     <l>Elſewhere is nought but emptineſs and lies.</l>
                     <l>Jehovah calls, the Father, and the Son;</l>
                     <l>The Holy Ghoſt, Bleſt Three, in Eſſence One.</l>
                     <l>Nothing but God, the Father, Son, and Spirit,</l>
                     <l>Can fit and fill thy Soul's vaſt appetite.</l>
                     <l>The Soul's a Spirit, and while not unite</l>
                     <l>To God, who is a Spirit Infinite,</l>
                     <l>It wandreth, ſeeking reſt, but findeth none,</l>
                     <l>Nor ought that gives it contentation.</l>
                     <l>Immortal Souls, in things which fade with time,</l>
                     <l>Cannot find reſt: Come reſtleſs ſoul to him</l>
                     <l>Who in Eternity hath his abode,</l>
                     <l>And is from and to everlaſting God;</l>
                     <l>Who changeth not, with whom is no mutation,</l>
                     <l>Nor any ſhadow of an alteration:</l>
                     <l>Who is, and was, and ſhall be ſtill the ſame,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Name alone is, <hi>I am that I am.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>When thy heart fails, thy hearts ſtrength he will be,</l>
                     <l>And thy ſure Portion to Eternity.</l>
                     <l>God Infinite in wiſdom, only wiſe,</l>
                     <l>Calls, Wilt thou, fool, Wiſdom's advice deſpiſe?</l>
                     <l>It's God Almighty who doth thee command,</l>
                     <l>Wilt thou, frail wretch, Omnipotence withſtand,</l>
                     <l>Since the moſt Holy calleth upon thee?</l>
                     <l>To diſobey were groſs profanity,</l>
                     <l>Since the moſt Juſt, moſt juſtly doth thee preſs,</l>
                     <l>To diſobey were meer unrighteouſneſs.</l>
                     <l>He who thee calls is good and gracious,</l>
                     <l>To anger ſlow, in mercy plenteous.</l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:150340:5"/>
                     <l>He's lovely, loving, Love, who calls on thee:</l>
                     <l>Wilt thou from love, grace, goodneſs, mercy flee?</l>
                     <l>He who doth call, moſt faithful is and true.</l>
                     <l>Truſt Truth it ſelf, and thou ſhalt never rue.</l>
                     <l>The Great Creator calls, whoſe Word did call</l>
                     <l>What was not, and of nothing formed all;</l>
                     <l>Who all thy Members wrought moſt curiouſly,</l>
                     <l>And form'd thy Spirit in the midſt of thee:</l>
                     <l>He gave, and ſtill he life to thee doth give.</l>
                     <l>Thou liv'ſt in him, wilt thou without him live?</l>
                     <l>Thou mov'ſt in him, from him move not away:</l>
                     <l>From him in whom thou go'ſt, go not aſtray:</l>
                     <l>In him thou doſt exiſt; and canſt thou be</l>
                     <l>Without him, who gives being unto thee?</l>
                     <l>Where art thou <hi>Adam,</hi> when the Lord doth cry,</l>
                     <l>Where's God, my Maker, Man ſhould then reply.</l>
                     <l>When he in whom thou liv'ſt, and doth conſiſt,</l>
                     <l>Commands, how dares thou for thy life reſiſt?</l>
                     <l>When he in whom thou mov'ſt doth thee command,</l>
                     <l>To come to him, how dares thou lingring ſtand?</l>
                     <l>Lord, what is Man, that thou ſo much ſhould'ſt make</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch a nothing, and ſuch knowledge take</l>
                     <l>Of Man, who is but duſt, and fading graſs,</l>
                     <l>And, which is worſe, a loathſome filthy Maſs</l>
                     <l>Of darkneſs, horror, luſt, profanity,</l>
                     <l>Unrighteouſneſs, of ſin and miſery;</l>
                     <l>Conceiv'd in ſin, form'd in iniquity,</l>
                     <l>A ſlave to divers luſts, luſts of the eye,</l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:150340:6"/>
                     <l>Luſts of the fleſh, and to the pride of life,</l>
                     <l>To anger, hatred, malice, wrath and ſtrife.</l>
                     <l>All in him is corrupt and vitiate;</l>
                     <l>His heart's deceitful, wicked, deſperate;</l>
                     <l>Eſtrang'd from God, ſtraying as ſoon as born;</l>
                     <l>Inclin'd to lies, apoſtate, and forlorn.</l>
                     <l>This Man, whom thou, O Lord, didſt once create</l>
                     <l>In thine own Image, in a happy ſtate,</l>
                     <l>Hath quite diſ-made himſelf: He who was light,</l>
                     <l>Is darkneſs now; he who was made upright,</l>
                     <l>Is now perverſe, ungodly and unjuſt,</l>
                     <l>Conform to Satan, to his will and luſt;</l>
                     <l>Without the Lord, under Gods curſe and wrath,</l>
                     <l>Liable to the firſt and ſecond death:</l>
                     <l>To plagues in this life, which were long to tell,</l>
                     <l>And to the eaſeleſs, endleſs pains of Hell.</l>
                     <l>Lord, what but Grace and Mercy could thee move</l>
                     <l>Upon thy hateful Foes to ſet ſuch love?</l>
                     <l>To ſpeak to them who hearken not to thee,</l>
                     <l>To follow them who from thy preſence flee:</l>
                     <l>To ſhew thy ſelf to them who ſhut their eyes</l>
                     <l>On thee, and turn them unto vanities:</l>
                     <l>To ſtretch thy arms to thoſe which turn their back,</l>
                     <l>And not their face to thee; and thus forſake</l>
                     <l>The Spring of living waters, and in vain,</l>
                     <l>Dig Ciſterns, which no waters can contain.</l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150340:6"/>
                     <l>To love the loathſome lying in their blood,</l>
                     <l>To overcome their evil with thy good.</l>
                     <l>Of theſe who ſought thee not, lo, thou art found:</l>
                     <l>Where ſin aboundeth, Grace doth more abound.</l>
                     <l>O wonderful, that thy delights ſhould be</l>
                     <l>With Sons of Men from all Eternity!</l>
                     <l>Since thou art Love, thy love muſt wondrous be,</l>
                     <l>For all is wonderful that is in thee.</l>
                     <l>Thy love, moſt High, doth far ſurpaſs in height</l>
                     <l>The higheſt reach of Men or Angels ſight:</l>
                     <l>Its endleſs length no finite eye can ſee;</l>
                     <l>For it is from and to Eternity.</l>
                     <l>But O the depth paſt diving! Who can ſound</l>
                     <l>How low Love ſtoops? O lowlineſs profound!</l>
                     <l>That the moſt High, who cloathed is with light,</l>
                     <l>To which none can approach, ſhould from the height</l>
                     <l>Of Glory, which doth Heaven of Heavens tranſcend,</l>
                     <l>Unto the lower parts of Earth deſcend,</l>
                     <l>To take up fallen Man; yea, to take on</l>
                     <l>Frail Humane Nature: So that now the Son</l>
                     <l>Of God is Man, the Word is Fleſh; and thus</l>
                     <l>Behold, God is become like one of us.</l>
                     <l>In likeneſs of Man's ſinful fleſh God ſent</l>
                     <l>His own, His only Son, with this intent,</l>
                     <l>That he for us an Offering ſhould be,</l>
                     <l>And bear our ſins in's body on the Tree.</l>
                     <l>All we like wandring ſheep had gone aſtray,</l>
                     <l>The Lord on him did our tranſgreſſions lay</l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:150340:7"/>
                     <l>The blameleſs Lamb dies for the Sheep who ſtray,</l>
                     <l>And did reſtore that he took not away.</l>
                     <l>He who is bleſt, did bear the curſe that we</l>
                     <l>Who curſed are, in him might bleſſed be.</l>
                     <l>He who knew no ſin, was made ſin for us,</l>
                     <l>That we in him might be made righteous.</l>
                     <l>The Prince of life did die, that ſo the dead</l>
                     <l>In ſins, might by his death be quickened.</l>
                     <l>He taken was, and bound to ſet us free,</l>
                     <l>He was condemn'd, that we abſolv'd might be.</l>
                     <l>He quietly did ſtripes and wounds endure,</l>
                     <l>That by his ſtripes he all our wounds might cure.</l>
                     <l>The trouble of his Soul, his Agony,</l>
                     <l>Procur'd our Peace, and Soul's Tranquility.</l>
                     <l>His Soul was exceeding ſorrowful,</l>
                     <l>That we might joy, that our joy might be full.</l>
                     <l>He was forſaken of his God, that we</l>
                     <l>Unto God's prefence might have acceſs free.</l>
                     <l>His blood was ſhed, Juſtice to ſatisfie,</l>
                     <l>To purge away all our iniquity.</l>
                     <l>His fleſh is meat, his blood is drink indeed,</l>
                     <l>On which poor hungry, thirſty ſouls may feed.</l>
                     <l>He's God and Man, a Mediator meet,</l>
                     <l>To make the Peace, and God, and Man unite.</l>
                     <l>The fullneſs of the Godhead, bodily,</l>
                     <l>Dwelleth in him, what then can wanting be?</l>
                     <l>He's full of Grace and Truth, that empty we,</l>
                     <l>May from his fullneſs have compleat ſupply.</l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:150340:7"/>
                     <l>To us a Child is born, a Son is given,</l>
                     <l>To us he came, di'd, roſe, and went to Heaven.</l>
                     <l>He's all for us, all who obey his call,</l>
                     <l>Shall find all in him, who fills all in all.</l>
                     <l>In him is all that needy ſouls require,</l>
                     <l>All their ſalvation, all their deſire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why ſtayeſt thou, O my ſoul? Canſt thou refuſe?</l>
                     <l>What ſayeſt thou? What pretend'ſt thou for excuſe?</l>
                     <l>Thy call is clear; thou maiſt, yea, thou muſt come,</l>
                     <l>Thy Soveraign calls, God faithful is, by whom</l>
                     <l>Thou called art unto Communion,</l>
                     <l>And Fellowſhip with Jeſus Chriſt his Son.</l>
                     <l>The Son invites thee, ſpreading out his Hands,</l>
                     <l>He ſhews himſelf, cries, knocks, and waiting ſtands:</l>
                     <l>Ho, every one who thirſteth, come, he cries;</l>
                     <l>Come, come; he double, triple multiplies:</l>
                     <l>Come unto me, hear, and your ſoul ſhall live;</l>
                     <l>Come, weary ſouls, I reſt to you will give.</l>
                     <l>The Spirit ſays, Come, whoſoever will;</l>
                     <l>Take living water freely, drink thy fill.</l>
                     <l>Thus thou muſt love, or hate; come, or rebel:</l>
                     <l>And all who hate Chriſt, love Death, Wrath, and Hell.</l>
                     <l>All who deſpiſe his Love, revenging Wrath</l>
                     <l>Shall them purſue unto Eternal Death.</l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:150340:8"/>
                     <l>Thus thou haſt heard his voice, now lift thine eyes,</l>
                     <l>Behold him, who, Behold, behold me, cries.</l>
                     <l>Behold the true God, who is over all,</l>
                     <l>God bleſt for ever, conſubſtantial.</l>
                     <l>With God the Father, God's own only Son,</l>
                     <l>The Father's daily delectation.</l>
                     <l>The brightneſs of the Father's Glory bright,</l>
                     <l>His Perſon's expreſs Image, light of light,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Immanuel,</hi> that's plainly, God with us,</l>
                     <l>God-Man, One Perſon Great and Gracious:</l>
                     <l>The Lord of Lords, the Prince and King of Kings,</l>
                     <l>The Sun of Righteouſneſs, who in his wings</l>
                     <l>Hath Healing; yea, hath Life; for he's the Light</l>
                     <l>Of Life, who gives unto the blind their ſight.</l>
                     <l>The great High-Prieſt, who by the Eternal Spirit,</l>
                     <l>Offered himſelf a Sacrifice compleat.</l>
                     <l>All in him lovely is, in him is all</l>
                     <l>That lovely is, All Good we ſhould him call.</l>
                     <l>He's God, yet Man, and near of kin to us;</l>
                     <l>Moſt High, yet lowly, Great, yet gracious.</l>
                     <l>We ſent not for him, yet behold he's come:</l>
                     <l>Think who he is, who cometh, and to whom</l>
                     <l>He had no need of nothings, who are leſs</l>
                     <l>Than nothing: Fullneſs comes to emptineſs.</l>
                     <l>We made the breach, we ſinned, yet his Grace</l>
                     <l>Prevents us, ſeeks our love, intreats for peace.</l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:150340:8"/>
                     <l>This Plot of Love the Goſpel doth reveal;</l>
                     <l>God was in Chriſt the world to reconcile</l>
                     <l>Unto himſelf, and then a Miniſtry</l>
                     <l>Of Reconciliation we do ſee</l>
                     <l>Intruſted to his Meſſengers of Peace,</l>
                     <l>To publiſh, and make Offers of his Grace.</l>
                     <l>If we his Meſſengers ſlight and abuſe,</l>
                     <l>We God himſelf deſpiſe, ſlight and refuſe.</l>
                     <l>He who deſpiſeth them, doth God contemn,</l>
                     <l>Since God himſelf beſeecheth us by them.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Again, my Soul, conſider thy eſtate,</l>
                     <l>While thou from Chriſt continues ſeparate:</l>
                     <l>Lo, thou art blind, naked, miſerable;</l>
                     <l>Thou canſt not help thy ſelf, but Chriſt is able</l>
                     <l>To help, and ſave, even to the uttermoſt,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe who are ſelf-deſtroyed, dead and loſt:</l>
                     <l>His Name is <hi>Jeſus:</hi> He did get that Name</l>
                     <l>Which ſpeaks ſalvation, becauſe he came</l>
                     <l>To ſave his people from their ſins, and from</l>
                     <l>The dreadful everlaſting wrath to come.</l>
                     <l>His Name is <hi>Christ,</hi> that is to ſay, anointed;</l>
                     <l>For he to ſave is fitted and appointed.</l>
                     <l>As it's his Office, ſo it is his Joy</l>
                     <l>To ſave the loſt, and Satan's works deſtroy.</l>
                     <l>If thou art poor, wouldſt thou do him a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure?</l>
                     <l>Come with thy emptineſs unto his Treaſure,</l>
                     <l>Where thou wilt find Riches unſearchable,</l>
                     <l>Fine tried Gold, and Subſtance durable.</l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:150340:9"/>
                     <l>Thy eyes are blind, come unto him; for he</l>
                     <l>Hath Eye-ſalve, which doth make the blind to ſee.</l>
                     <l>Art thou aſham'd of thy vile nakedneſs?</l>
                     <l>Here's fine white Raiment, perfect Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</l>
                     <l>Thou art a Fool, of wiſdom deſtitute,</l>
                     <l>Like a wild Aſſes Colt, a ſtupid Bruit.</l>
                     <l>Lo he is wiſdom, and is wiſdom made</l>
                     <l>Unto the fooliſh, who no wiſdom had.</l>
                     <l>Thou art by Nature darkneſs of the Night;</l>
                     <l>He is that light which maketh darkneſs light.</l>
                     <l>Thou erreſt and wandreſt, going ſtill aſtray,</l>
                     <l>He is the truth, the leader, and the way;</l>
                     <l>The way of life, the true new living way,</l>
                     <l>By which unto the Holieſt come we may;</l>
                     <l>And by the blood of Jeſus, which makes peace,</l>
                     <l>With confidence may acceſs have to Grace.</l>
                     <l>The true, the faithful witneſs, the <hi>Amen,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is given for a leader unto men.</l>
                     <l>A juſt Commander, and a gracious Guide,</l>
                     <l>From ſtrangers on the Earth he will not hide,</l>
                     <l>But open up the Scripture, clear the Eye</l>
                     <l>Of th' Underſtanding, Scripture-light to ſee.</l>
                     <l>The light of truth he unto them doth ſhow,</l>
                     <l>That truth from error they may clearly know.</l>
                     <l>He ſhows what's right, what's wrong, what's good, what's ill,</l>
                     <l>For to inform the Mind, reform the Will.</l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:150340:9"/>
                     <l>He takes them by the arms, learns them to go,</l>
                     <l>And holds them, that they reel not to and fro.</l>
                     <l>If thou art weak, thy help on him is laid,</l>
                     <l>Who mighty is, in ſtraits a preſent aid.</l>
                     <l>Thou filthy art without, unclean within,</l>
                     <l>He is a Fountain opened for ſin.</l>
                     <l>Thou art diſeaſed, this Phyſician can</l>
                     <l>Heal all Diſeaſes incident to Man.</l>
                     <l>This Man's the Peace in midſt of Enemies,</l>
                     <l>The heart's ſupport under Infirmities:</l>
                     <l>He is the Ark in midſt of a Deluge,</l>
                     <l>When wrath purſues a City of Refuge.</l>
                     <l>If thou art dead, he's life; if loſt, ſalvation;</l>
                     <l>If comfortleſs, he's <hi>Iſrael's</hi> conſolation.</l>
                     <l>Jeſus is All, by Jeſus Name alone,</l>
                     <l>To Men is given God's ſalvation.</l>
                     <l>All they which are in him are juſtified,</l>
                     <l>Regenerate, adopted, glorified.</l>
                     <l>Come, come to him, and then thou ſhalt be free</l>
                     <l>From condemnation, and accepted be,</l>
                     <l>As Juſt, through his Obedience to the Death,</l>
                     <l>Imputed to thee, and receiv'd by Faith.</l>
                     <l>Thy ſins and guilt ſhall never thee confound,</l>
                     <l>Though they be ſought for, they ſhall not be found.</l>
                     <l>They are renew'd who are in him that's true,</l>
                     <l>Old things are paſt, and all things are made new.</l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:150340:10"/>
                     <l>Chriſt lives in them, and Chriſt in them is found,</l>
                     <l>And to his Image they are all conform'd.</l>
                     <l>They die to ſin, they live to him who died,</l>
                     <l>And roſe, that they might be all ſanctified.</l>
                     <l>As many as receive him, who doth come</l>
                     <l>To them, they all the Sons of God become:</l>
                     <l>They have his Spirit, they have acceſs free</l>
                     <l>To Grace, and <hi>Abba, Father,</hi> they may cry:</l>
                     <l>They by his Name are call'd, by him protected,</l>
                     <l>Provided for, they'r chaſt'ned and corrected;</l>
                     <l>Yet not caſt off; their Father's power and love</l>
                     <l>Keeps-them to their inheritance above:</l>
                     <l>They all are Heirs of life perpetual,</l>
                     <l>Heirs and joynt-heirs with Chriſt, the Heir of all.</l>
                     <l>They perſevere, and never fall away</l>
                     <l>From Grace, in which they firmly ſtand for ay.</l>
                     <l>For God's Foundation ſtandeth ever ſure;</l>
                     <l>He knows his own, his love doth ſtill endure.</l>
                     <l>There's none, there's nothing whatſoever that</l>
                     <l>Them from the love of Chriſt can ſeperate.</l>
                     <l>He will not leave them, he doth promiſe make,</l>
                     <l>That he will not them leave, nor them forſake.</l>
                     <l>They ſhall not leave the Lord, for in their heart</l>
                     <l>He puts his fear, that they may not depart.</l>
                     <l>None can them pluck away, they firmly ſtand,</l>
                     <l>As holden in the Son's and Father's Hand.</l>
                     <l>Chriſt's Interceſſion, which doth ſtill prevail,</l>
                     <l>Procureth, that their Faith ſhall never fail.</l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:150340:10"/>
                     <l>They perſevere in Grace, in Grace they grow;</l>
                     <l>From Chriſt in them moe benefits do flow:</l>
                     <l>Aſſurance of God's favour and his grace,</l>
                     <l>In midſt of trouble, inward reſt and peace</l>
                     <l>Of Conſcience, the joy of God's ſalvation,</l>
                     <l>Which makes them glory, even in tribulation.</l>
                     <l>Their Souls at death are perfectly made free</l>
                     <l>From ſin to glory, paſs immediately:</l>
                     <l>Their bodies ſleep in Chriſt, in whom they have</l>
                     <l>Reſt till the Reſurrection in the grave.</l>
                     <l>Then their vile body, ſo by Death deform'd,</l>
                     <l>Shall to Chriſt's glorious body be conform'd,</l>
                     <l>The Soul and Body being unite ſhall be</l>
                     <l>For ever with the Lord, and clearly ſee</l>
                     <l>His Glory in his Light; they ſhall ſee Light:</l>
                     <l>There is no darkneſs there, there is no Night:</l>
                     <l>Shadows are fled, the Latteſs here below</l>
                     <l>Did well, through which the Lord himſelf did ſhow.</l>
                     <l>But when the perfect day is come, and grace</l>
                     <l>Is crown'd with glory, they ſee face to face,</l>
                     <l>Not in a glaſs, nothing doth interveen,</l>
                     <l>To mar their ſight, they ſee as they are ſeen,</l>
                     <l>And known; there needs no Candle there,</l>
                     <l>Nor Moon, nor Sun, theſe lights are darkneſs where</l>
                     <l>God's Glory ſhines, and where the Lamb's the light:</l>
                     <l>He fills the eye, and perfect makes the ſight.</l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:150340:11"/>
                     <l>In his own glory, they his glory ſee,</l>
                     <l>And like him are, becauſe they perfectly</l>
                     <l>Behold him as he is: The Light Divine</l>
                     <l>Inlightens them, that like the Sun they ſhine.</l>
                     <l>They ſee his love, it's in their heart and eye,</l>
                     <l>That he is God, their Soul doth taſte and ſee;</l>
                     <l>And in his love, the Spring of Life Divine,</l>
                     <l>They Water drink that's better far than Wine</l>
                     <l>Rivers of pleaſures in upon them flow,</l>
                     <l>And fill their Soul throughout, and overflow,</l>
                     <l>Yet do not drown: Theſe living waters give</l>
                     <l>Eternal life to all who in them live.</l>
                     <l>Their love is perfect, God's love makes abode</l>
                     <l>In them, they dwell in love, and dwell in God.</l>
                     <l>And then a whole Burnt-offering they prove,</l>
                     <l>Wholly inflam'd, but not conſum'd by love.</l>
                     <l>They'r free from ſin, free from all that defiles,</l>
                     <l>From all temptations, from all Satan's wiles;</l>
                     <l>No ſpot remains, Holineſs is perfect.</l>
                     <l>Here they lov'd cleanneſs, there they wake in white.</l>
                     <l>No trouble's there, diſhonour, nor diſgrace,</l>
                     <l>But perfect Glory, Honour, Reſt and Peace:</l>
                     <l>There is no grief, nor ought that can annoy,</l>
                     <l>Chriſt's Joy's in them, they enter into Joy.</l>
                     <l>No doubts perplex them, nor ſuſpicious fear,</l>
                     <l>For God's Name is in all their Fore-heads clear.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Come now to Chriſt, and then he unto whom</l>
                     <l>Thou comeſt, will kindly thee invite to come</l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:150340:11"/>
                     <l>Into his Kingdom; yea, he will thee own,</l>
                     <l>As a Joynt-Heir, and thee with Glory Crown.</l>
                     <l>And (which doth paſs all admiration)</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt be fet with him upon his Throne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>They who will not come now, muſt then be gone</l>
                     <l>From Chriſt to Hell, and to deſtruction.</l>
                     <l>For when the Lord, whom now they will not hear,</l>
                     <l>Shall as great Judge at the great day appear.</l>
                     <l>His words ſhall thunder terror through their heart,</l>
                     <l>When they ſhall hear the dreadful Doom, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part,</l>
                     <l>Depart, ye curſt, to fire unquenchable,</l>
                     <l>With Satan and his Angels execrable,</l>
                     <l>Where there is endleſs weeping, fruitleſs tears,</l>
                     <l>Gnaſhing of teeth through anguiſh, and where fears,</l>
                     <l>Conſuming terrors, horrors do abound,</l>
                     <l>Shame and contempt eternally confound:</l>
                     <l>There they who would not look to Chriſt the Light,</l>
                     <l>Shall be for ever ſhut out from his ſight.</l>
                     <l>In utter darkneſs, in an endleſs night,</l>
                     <l>Blackneſs of darkneſs ſhall them ſtill affright.</l>
                     <l>They who deſpiſe his love, ſhall drink his wrath,</l>
                     <l>And ſtreams of Brimſtone kindled by his breath.</l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:150340:12"/>
                     <l>The wine is wrath, the wrath of God without</l>
                     <l>All Mixture, is unto them pour'd out</l>
                     <l>Of Divine Indignation's dreadful Cup.</l>
                     <l>They ſwallow wrath, and wrath them ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows up,</l>
                     <l>With wrath and fury they are fill'd and drunk,</l>
                     <l>And in a lake of fire and brimeſtone ſunk:</l>
                     <l>Their torments ſmoak aſcendeth up for ever,</l>
                     <l>They have no reſt, their torment ceaſeth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now life and death are ſet before thee, chuſe</l>
                     <l>What thou wilt take, &amp; what thou wilt refuſe.</l>
                     <l>Wilt thou, fool, turn eternal life to death?</l>
                     <l>Wilt thou refuſe God's favour, chuſe his wrath?</l>
                     <l>And turn from Jeſus Chriſt to go to Devils?</l>
                     <l>Refuſe all good, and chuſe all ſorts of evils?</l>
                     <l>Darkneſs prefer to light, wilt thou refuſe</l>
                     <l>Rivers of pleaſures, ſtreams of brimſtone chuſe?</l>
                     <l>If thou the God of Truth, Love, Mercy, Grace,</l>
                     <l>Forſake, and lying vanities embrace,</l>
                     <l>Thy conſcience, the worm that doth not die,</l>
                     <l>Shall torture thee to all eternity.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now tell me, Soul, what thy Objections are:</l>
                     <l>Is it Chriſt's Yoke, Rod, Croſs, that doth thee ſcare?</l>
                     <l>His Yoke is eaſie, and his Burthen light,</l>
                     <l>His Laws not grievous, but the Soul's delight;</l>
                     <l>All his Commandments are holy, juſt &amp; good,</l>
                     <l>And better far than thy appointed food.</l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:150340:12"/>
                     <l>They ſweeter than the Honey-Comb ſhall prove;</l>
                     <l>For all his Laws are ſummed up in love.</l>
                     <l>The love of God, who is the chiefeſt good,</l>
                     <l>And of our Neighbour, our own fleſh and blood.</l>
                     <l>To the in hatred is on Earth a Hell,</l>
                     <l>But it's a Heaven on Earth in love to dwell.</l>
                     <l>Shouldſt thou not love the Lord with all thy heart,</l>
                     <l>Who goodneſs is, and doth good impart?</l>
                     <l>With all thy ſoul, ſince he's the God alone</l>
                     <l>Which to the ſoul gives ſatisfaction?</l>
                     <l>With all the mind? for he doth fill the mind,</l>
                     <l>And cannot be by finite thoughts confin'd.</l>
                     <l>With all thy ſtrength? Thy Powers are not able</l>
                     <l>Him to deſire as he is deſirable,</l>
                     <l>Tho all thy ſoul to th' utmoſt thou extend,</l>
                     <l>It cannot boundleſs goodneſs comprehend.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Love ſweetly joins the heart to God alone,</l>
                     <l>And other gods before him will have none.</l>
                     <l>It will have none on Earth or Heaven above,</l>
                     <l>But God for its deſire, delight and love.</l>
                     <l>The Spouſe diſdains (this is love's holy pride)</l>
                     <l>By Chriſt's companions to turn aſide.</l>
                     <l>To pleaſe the Lord love doth the ſoul diſpoſe,</l>
                     <l>And with his will in every thing to cloſe.</l>
                     <l>Love worſhip's God according to his mind,</l>
                     <l>And loves to be within his will confin'd.</l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:150340:13"/>
                     <l>Love fears his Jealouſie, and ſtands in awe,</l>
                     <l>To take ought from, or add ought to his Law.</l>
                     <l>It caſts all worſhip forged by man's will,</l>
                     <l>And doth the ſale of Idol-mongers ſpill.</l>
                     <l>Love God; and then his glorious Name to thee</l>
                     <l>As precious Ointment poured out will be.</l>
                     <l>Strongly, yet ſweetly Love will thee reſtrain</l>
                     <l>From taking his moſt holy Name in vain.</l>
                     <l>Love God, ſo Sabbath-days from morn till night,</l>
                     <l>Shall be by thee accounted a delight.</l>
                     <l>Theſe Sabbaths of the Lord are holy bleſt,</l>
                     <l>Love's triſting times, Feaſt-days, and days of Reſt.</l>
                     <l>Then the beloved bleſſeth Saints with grace</l>
                     <l>And glory, then they ſee his lovely face.</l>
                     <l>He entertaineth them in holy reſt;</l>
                     <l>Days in his Courts of all days are the beſt.</l>
                     <l>From love to God neighbourly love doth flow,</l>
                     <l>From this ſweet root this pleaſant plant doth grow.</l>
                     <l>Since man was made in Gods ſimilitude,</l>
                     <l>Since all men are of the ſame fleſh and blood,</l>
                     <l>It's for God's honour, and our own behoof,</l>
                     <l>That we our Neighbour as our ſelves ſhould love.</l>
                     <l>The light of Nature cries it's righteous,</l>
                     <l>To do as we would men to do to us.</l>
                     <l>If thou thy neighbour love, thou wilt delight</l>
                     <l>To keep him blameleſs, and to do him right.</l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:150340:13"/>
                     <l>Love turns Superiors to Fathers kind,</l>
                     <l>And makes them of a condeſcending mind.</l>
                     <l>Love bounds their wrath, moves to commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</l>
                     <l>Love tempers rigour, pleads for moderation.</l>
                     <l>When Juſtice, matcht with Mercy, ſweetly reign,</l>
                     <l>Then all of Juſtice, and of Mercy ſing.</l>
                     <l>Bleſt is the land in which the law of love</l>
                     <l>Doth rule in thoſe below and thoſe above.</l>
                     <l>Love maketh Equals deal with one another,</l>
                     <l>As every one were one another's brother.</l>
                     <l>Where Love prevaileth in inferiors,</l>
                     <l>It makes them kindly honour higher powers.</l>
                     <l>Love envies not ſuperiors higher place,</l>
                     <l>But doth in God's Order ſtill acquieſce.</l>
                     <l>Love maketh Subjects patient and mild,</l>
                     <l>Like to a kindly tender hearted child,</l>
                     <l>Who tho injur'd with grief and ſhamefac'dneſs,</l>
                     <l>Conceals his Father's faults and nakedneſs.</l>
                     <l>Love maketh man abhor man's blood to ſhed,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ince God hath man in his own Image made.</l>
                     <l>To ſinful Anger, Hatred, Envy, Spite,</l>
                     <l>Malice, Revenge, Love is moſt oppoſite.</l>
                     <l>Pure love deſtroys vile filthy luſts, and flies</l>
                     <l>From Fornications and Adulteries.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t purifies the heart, and guards the eye,</l>
                     <l>And will not wrong a Neighbour's chaſtity.</l>
                     <l>He who is loving, ſeeks his Neighbour's wealth,</l>
                     <l>And wrongeth none by Rapine or by ſtealth.</l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:150340:14"/>
                     <l>Love is moſt tender of a Neighbour's Name,</l>
                     <l>It thinks no evil, and will not defame;</l>
                     <l>It loveth truth, and doth abhor all lies,</l>
                     <l>Falſe-witneſſing, reproaches, calumnies.</l>
                     <l>Love is contented well with its own lot,</l>
                     <l>And what belongs to others covets not.</l>
                     <l>It's oppoſite to the firſt inclinations,</l>
                     <l>Which tend to ill, to ſinful delectations.</l>
                     <l>Since Love's the end, and ſum of all the Law,</l>
                     <l>It's pleaſant in Love's eaſie yoak to draw,</l>
                     <l>The Law of Love is holy, good and juſt;</l>
                     <l>But Oh! the lawleſs Law of ſin and luſt,</l>
                     <l>Like to a ſtinking humour ſpoils the taſte</l>
                     <l>Of Luſt-ſick men, that the ſweet food diſtaſte,</l>
                     <l>To man's ſtiff Neck, which galling luſt doth ſpoil,</l>
                     <l>The Yoak ſeems hard, which ſofter is than Oil.</l>
                     <l>Yea, no meer man is able ſince the Fall</l>
                     <l>To keep theſe perfect Laws, but breaks them all:</l>
                     <l>And every ſin deſerves God's curſe and wrath</l>
                     <l>Both in this preſent life and after death.</l>
                     <l>Yet, O poor ſinner, turn not deſperate,</l>
                     <l>Since with the Father there's an Advocate,</l>
                     <l>Even Jeſus Chriſt the Righteouss who hath</l>
                     <l>Fulfill'd the Law, appeas'd revenging wrath.</l>
                     <l>He hath the Law eſtabliſht, anſwered</l>
                     <l>All that it did demand, or threatned.</l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150340:14"/>
                     <l>Juſtice hath found a Ranſom in the Son,</l>
                     <l>Full ſatisfaction for tranſgreſſion.</l>
                     <l>He under lay the curſe, that he might free</l>
                     <l>All from the curſe who unto him do flee.</l>
                     <l>Come unto him who is the Lord's ſalvation,</l>
                     <l>And thou ſhalt not come into condemnation.</l>
                     <l>For all ſins of omiſſion and commiſſion</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt receive a full and free remiſſion.</l>
                     <l>He will take off thy rags of filthineſs,</l>
                     <l>And cloath thee with white robes of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</l>
                     <l>Was ever Traitor ſo perverfly mad,</l>
                     <l>To ſlight a pardon when it might be had?</l>
                     <l>To ſeek for cautioneis poor debters run:</l>
                     <l>Wilt thou an able off'red Surety ſhun?</l>
                     <l>Art thou with ſins too heavy burden preſt?</l>
                     <l>Come, weary ſoul, and Chriſt ſhall give thee reſt.</l>
                     <l>Art thou for foughten, and quite out of breath</l>
                     <l>With the old man, that man of ſin and death?</l>
                     <l>Groan unto him, that he may pity thee:</l>
                     <l>Say, I'm oppreſt, Lord, undertake for me.</l>
                     <l>He who cri'd out, <hi>O wretched man am I,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Within a little ſung of Victory.</l>
                     <l>Cry, Help, Lord, ſins prevail againſt me, do;</l>
                     <l>Purge me, ſubdue them, and them quite undo.</l>
                     <l>Since without him thou canſt do nothing right,</l>
                     <l>Be ſtrong in him, in the power of his might.</l>
                     <l>When thou com'ſt up out of the wilderneſs,</l>
                     <l>Lean upon him, lean on him all thy ſtreſs.</l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:150340:15"/>
                     <l>Would thou have peace and comfort, come to Jeſus:</l>
                     <l>He is the peace, and he alone can eaſe us.</l>
                     <l>By Faith receive him to dwell in thy heart:</l>
                     <l>He will thy conſcience purge, and eaſe its ſmart.</l>
                     <l>Take him as off'red in the Goſpel-Call:</l>
                     <l>With this great gift the Father giveth all.</l>
                     <l>Stay wholly on him, reſt on him alone</l>
                     <l>For to accompliſh thy ſalvation;</l>
                     <l>To ſave thee from all ſin and miſery,</l>
                     <l>And with all goodneſs thee to ſatisfie.</l>
                     <l>Is not this work of Faith the hearts delight?</l>
                     <l>Is not this labour eaſe? this burden light?</l>
                     <l>A hungry thirſty man will never think,</l>
                     <l>That it's a grievous work to eat and drink.</l>
                     <l>It's eaſing to a man with loads oppreſt,</l>
                     <l>To be disburden'd, and to find a reſt.</l>
                     <l>The wind toſt traveller is glad to find</l>
                     <l>A hiding place, to hide him from the wind.</l>
                     <l>And they whom a tempeſtuous ſtorm doth beat,</l>
                     <l>With pleaſure to a covert make retreat.</l>
                     <l>Tho thirſty, when in a dry place they ſee</l>
                     <l>Rivers of waters, thither they will flee.</l>
                     <l>If travellers ſee a great high Rock ſtand</l>
                     <l>In a Sun burnt, and ſcorched weary land,</l>
                     <l>Tho they be weary, yet they mend their pace,</l>
                     <l>To find in its cool ſhadow ſome ſolace.</l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:150340:15"/>
                     <l>The drowning man longs at the Rock to be,</l>
                     <l>The chaſed man into a ſtrength doth flee,</l>
                     <l>Yet all theſe things, when they together twiſt,</l>
                     <l>Are but meer ſhadows when compar'd with Chriſt.</l>
                     <l>He is the Truth, true Light, true Life, true Food,</l>
                     <l>A refuge from all ill: He's all that's good.</l>
                     <l>To buy this Pearl all things are wiſely ſold;</l>
                     <l>For it's a treaſure that cannot be told.</l>
                     <l>Riches unſearchable in Chriſt do meet:</l>
                     <l>In this one Pearl all treaſures are unite.</l>
                     <l>Earth's Riches, upon which poor worldlings dote,</l>
                     <l>Tho they appear to be, yet they are not:</l>
                     <l>They are uncertain, yea, uncertainty,</l>
                     <l>And certainly they will make wings and fly:</l>
                     <l>They are but ſhadows when they ſeem to ſtay,</l>
                     <l>And are found nothing when they flee away.</l>
                     <l>Theſe many things to nothing do amount,</l>
                     <l>When in Death's ſhadow men caſt the account.</l>
                     <l>Oft-times in life theſe Riches take their wing;</l>
                     <l>When death is come, they ſignifie nothing,</l>
                     <l>Except to vex the rich, they cannot free</l>
                     <l>From death, nor him in death accompany.</l>
                     <l>But here true wealth, riches unſearchable,</l>
                     <l>Eternal riches, ſubſtance durable.</l>
                     <l>With many things vex not thy heart or head,</l>
                     <l>Since in one Pearl all good is treaſured.</l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:150340:16"/>
                     <l>Reſt not in hear-ſay, come, himſelf behold,</l>
                     <l>And thou ſhalt ſee much more than hath been told.</l>
                     <l>Buy without price, or money, O! cheap rate,</l>
                     <l>And calculate for our poor mean eſtate.</l>
                     <l>Sure it's free grace which hath this match made,</l>
                     <l>Where all things good may be for nothing had.</l>
                     <l>Put to thy hand, fear not, thou maiſt be bold,</l>
                     <l>Since he himſelf commands thee to take hold.</l>
                     <l>Since ſweetneſs, better, by the taſte than eye,</l>
                     <l>Or ear is known, O come! and taſte and ſee,</l>
                     <l>How good the Lord is: eat that which is good,</l>
                     <l>Fatneſs and Marrow, ſoul-delighting food.</l>
                     <l>Drink wine that's well refined on the Lees,</l>
                     <l>Drink poverty away and miſeries.</l>
                     <l>Be filled with the Spirit, do not fear,</l>
                     <l>Leſt thou exceed, there is no exceſs here:</l>
                     <l>Drink, thirſty ſoul, and drink abundantly:</l>
                     <l>He who drinks moſt, liveth moſt ſoberly.</l>
                     <l>This drink doth not the ſence and head con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found,</l>
                     <l>It clears the eyes, makes mind and judgment ſound:</l>
                     <l>It doth not pervert, but right the heart,</l>
                     <l>And from all evil to all good convert.</l>
                     <l>They reel not; for the Spirit doth them lead,</l>
                     <l>They ſafely go, their paths are ſtabliſhed.</l>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:150340:16"/>
                     <l>Their Mirth's not madneſs, it is ſolid, pure;</l>
                     <l>Ends not in ſadneſs, but doth ſtill endure.</l>
                     <l>They who are filled with the Spirit, rejoice,</l>
                     <l>Make melody to God with heart and voice.</l>
                     <l>They Pſalms, and Hymns, and Spiritual Songs do ſing,</l>
                     <l>Give thanks to God, through Chriſt, in every thing.</l>
                     <l>Theſe Joys begin the perfect melody,</l>
                     <l>Which is above; come, taſte, and ſing, and ſee.</l>
                     <l>Ah carnal wretch, who knows no other Feaſts,</l>
                     <l>But ſuch as common are to men with beaſts:</l>
                     <l>Who ſeeks no better meat, nor better drink,</l>
                     <l>Than what corrupts, and turns to filth and ſtink.</l>
                     <l>Thy belly is thy God, thy glory ſhame,</l>
                     <l>Thy pleaſure is the ſhadow of a dream,</l>
                     <l>Which goes in coming, when it comes it goes,</l>
                     <l>And leaves a filthy ſtain upon the ſoul;</l>
                     <l>It leaves a ſting for thy vexation</l>
                     <l>And guilt, which binds to condemnation.</l>
                     <l>Thy momentary mirth, thy pleaſures vain,</l>
                     <l>Brings on moſt real and eternal pain.</l>
                     <l>Thy fill is emptineſs, thy mirth is madneſs,</l>
                     <l>The laughter of a fool that ends in ſadneſs.</l>
                     <l>Thy fleſhly luſts, tho they ſeem to delight,</l>
                     <l>Againſt thy ſoul moſt fiercely they do fight.</l>
                     <l>Their fond embraces are death's cruel graſps:</l>
                     <l>Their ſeeming ſweetneſs is the gall of Aſps.</l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:150340:17"/>
                     <l>The money's ſpent for that which is no bread,</l>
                     <l>But is the bane whereby thou'rt poiſoned.</l>
                     <l>Thy labour's ſpent for vexing vanity,</l>
                     <l>Which doth torment, but cannot ſatisfie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When wilt thou come unto thy ſelf, and ſay,</l>
                     <l>Ah! I am famiſhed, I pine away</l>
                     <l>With hunger; I am cheated, poiſoned:</l>
                     <l>I feed vile luſts, by them I'm murthered.</l>
                     <l>I hear of bread indeed, and bread to ſpare,</l>
                     <l>And of a Feaſt, where all things ready are.</l>
                     <l>Since I am called, ſhall I not make haſte,</l>
                     <l>And run before I die? But Oh! the Feaſt,</l>
                     <l>And the Feaſt-maker, are juſt at my hand,</l>
                     <l>Before the door, tho cloſed he doth ſtand.</l>
                     <l>He knocks, and doth me lovingly invite:</l>
                     <l>Since he's ſo near, alas! ſhall we not meet?</l>
                     <l>If any man what ere he was before,</l>
                     <l>My voice hear, and to me open the door,</l>
                     <l>I will come in, and ſup with; if he,</l>
                     <l>Poor thing have nothing, he ſhall ſup with me.</l>
                     <l>Theſe are his words, if I had ears to hear,</l>
                     <l>Lord, open them, give me the hearing ear.</l>
                     <l>Since, Lord, thou art ſo near, do not depart:</l>
                     <l>Stand not without, ah! ſhall a door us part:</l>
                     <l>Make the King's Keys, or ſince thou'rt not for breaking,</l>
                     <l>Right the ſplit lock, it is of thine own making.</l>
                     <l>I have it ſplit, it will not budge nor gee</l>
                     <l>For any thing that can be done by me.</l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:150340:17"/>
                     <l>Lord, thou canſt mend it, put thy hand within,</l>
                     <l>Open my cloſed heart, thou know'ſt the gin:</l>
                     <l>When <hi>David</hi>'s Key in thy Almighty Hand,</l>
                     <l>Doth open, none can ſhut, or thee withſtand.</l>
                     <l>Come in, O mighty one, and diſpoſſeſs</l>
                     <l>Satan and Luſt, which do my ſoul oppreſs.</l>
                     <l>Of thy own goodneſs, Lord, the Feaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide,</l>
                     <l>Enlarge my heart, and my mouth open wide,</l>
                     <l>And fill it; for both hunger and the fill</l>
                     <l>Proceed from the good pleaſure of thy will.</l>
                     <l>Without thee I am nothing, nothing have,</l>
                     <l>And nothing good can think, will, do, or crave,</l>
                     <l>Unleſs thy Spirit help my infirmity,</l>
                     <l>And grace perfect all that concerneth me.</l>
                     <l>I cannot come, except that I drawn be:</l>
                     <l>Draw me, O Lord, and I will come to thee</l>
                     <l>O wretched ſinner, cry for mercy, cry,</l>
                     <l>When Chriſt, the Son of <hi>David,</hi> is ſo nigh.</l>
                     <l>Blind <hi>Bartimeus</hi> heard that Chriſt paſt by:</l>
                     <l>He takes the tide, and doth for Mercy cry.</l>
                     <l>Many did think his crying a diſgrace,</l>
                     <l>And charged him, that he ſhould hold his peace.</l>
                     <l>But he the more did lift his voice and cry,</l>
                     <l>O Son of <hi>David,</hi> mercy have on me.</l>
                     <l>Jeſus ſtood ſtill, he thought it not a ſhame</l>
                     <l>To be thus call'd, but anſwer'd to his Name.</l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:150340:18"/>
                     <l>The Beggar being called, made no ſtay,</l>
                     <l>But in his haſte, did caſt his Cloak away.</l>
                     <l>He ſeeks for ſight, obtaineth his requeſt:</l>
                     <l>He came in faith, in love he follows Chriſt.</l>
                     <l>Let nothing which Devils or Men can ſay,</l>
                     <l>Scare thee; caſt all impediments away.</l>
                     <l>Since the great Maſter calls, make no delay,</l>
                     <l>Turn a deaf ear to all, who him gain-ſay.</l>
                     <l>Do as the woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> did,</l>
                     <l>From whom Chriſt, tho retir'd, could not be hid:</l>
                     <l>She crieth out, <hi>Have mercy on me, Lord:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Chriſt hears her cry, but anſwers not a word.</l>
                     <l>And when he ſpeaks, his words diſcourage more</l>
                     <l>Than did the ſilence which he kept before:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I am not ſent but to</hi> Iſrael<hi>'s loſt ſheep,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Says Chriſt: The woman will not dive ſo deep,</l>
                     <l>To diſpute his Commiſſions extent,</l>
                     <l>To whom he was, to whom he was not ſent;</l>
                     <l>But kindly came, and humbly him ador'd,</l>
                     <l>Preſt her ſuit, and cries out, <hi>Help me, O Lord.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It is not meet to cast to dogs the bread,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Says Chriſt, <hi>with which the children ſhould be fed.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>She ſtorms not at a Dog's diſgraceful Name,</l>
                     <l>But wifely makes advantage of the ſame:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Since I'm a dog,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>for crumbs I plead:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Give me ſome crumbs, Lord, of children's bread.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:150340:18"/>
                     <l>Chriſt praiſed her great faith, and did fulfil</l>
                     <l>All her deſire, and gave her all her will.</l>
                     <l>Tho Chriſt withdraw, ſeek him, he will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear:</l>
                     <l>He hears thy cry when he ſeems not to hear.</l>
                     <l>Tho he ſeem ſtrange, unto him kindly come:</l>
                     <l>Tho thou be call'd a dog, yet ſeek a crumb.</l>
                     <l>If Satan ſay, thou art a reprobate,</l>
                     <l>That by a diſpute dark and intricate,</l>
                     <l>Concerning ſecret things, and depths pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found,</l>
                     <l>He may affright thee, and thy mind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found.</l>
                     <l>Liſten not to a lying murthering cheat;</l>
                     <l>Enter not with him on that great debate.</l>
                     <l>Come on, Chriſt's call, effectual vocation,</l>
                     <l>Will free thee from the fears of reprobation.</l>
                     <l>All whom he draws, are called in effect,</l>
                     <l>And were from all Eternity elect.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But if thou ſay, I fear the bitter ſmart</l>
                     <l>Of a repenting prickt, rent, broken heart,</l>
                     <l>I muſt confeſs my ſins with grief and tears,</l>
                     <l>And watch againſt my luſts with careful fears.</l>
                     <l>And thus my mirth is marr'd, and my glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</l>
                     <l>Is turn'd to grief and melancholly ſadneſs.</l>
                     <l>I anſwer that it is of God's free grace,</l>
                     <l>That for repentance there is any place.</l>
                     <l>Juſtice might ſay, go weep in Hell, and burn:</l>
                     <l>It's grace that ſays, Sinner, repent and turn.</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:150340:19"/>
                     <l>The pricking of the heart lets out the ſin,</l>
                     <l>Which feſters and deſtroys when kept within.</l>
                     <l>It's for thy health, that thy hard heart be rent,</l>
                     <l>That ſo thy vile impoſtume may be vent.</l>
                     <l>It's not a Foe's, but a Phyſician's wound:</l>
                     <l>God breaks the heart to make it whole and ſound.</l>
                     <l>The Lord doth heal the broken in their heart,</l>
                     <l>Their pain is gain, there's pleaſure in the ſmart.</l>
                     <l>There's peace and ſafety in their watchful fears;</l>
                     <l>The Oil of Joy is mixt with Goſpel-tears.</l>
                     <l>The Lord is broken by our whoriſh heart:</l>
                     <l>Should not our heart then break with grief and ſmart?</l>
                     <l>When Chriſt was bound, our ſins did make the bands,</l>
                     <l>They were the Nails that pierc'd his feet and hands;</l>
                     <l>They were the Thorns that tore and rent his head;</l>
                     <l>They were the Spear that made his heart to bleed.</l>
                     <l>The laſhing Whips, the Fiſts that did him beat,</l>
                     <l>They made his body weep a bloody ſweat.</l>
                     <l>His outward pains, the Agony within,</l>
                     <l>His troubled ſoul, procured were by ſin.</l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:150340:19"/>
                     <l>Look on him whom thou pierced, Oh! look on ſtill,</l>
                     <l>That grief thy heart, and tears thine eyes may fill;</l>
                     <l>That kindly thou maiſt weep and mourn, like one</l>
                     <l>Who mourneth for a firſt and only Son.</l>
                     <l>Sin is againſt the Lord, breaks his laws;</l>
                     <l>It mars his Image, and from God withdraws.</l>
                     <l>Thy ſin doth vex and grieve the holy Sp'rit:</l>
                     <l>Should thou with grief for ſin contrite.</l>
                     <l>They ſhall find mercy, who confeſs and turn;</l>
                     <l>Comfort is promiſed to theſe who mourn.</l>
                     <l>The Oil of Joy the Lord for mourning gives,</l>
                     <l>And he the humble contrite heart revives.</l>
                     <l>If godly ſorrow will not thee deſtroy,</l>
                     <l>It tends to life, its tears are ſeeds of joy.</l>
                     <l>Goſpel-grief, which melts the heart aright,</l>
                     <l>Is ſweeter far than all the world's delight.</l>
                     <l>And even godly grief, the ſweeter then</l>
                     <l>All the delights of all the ſons of men,</l>
                     <l>Who can the peace of God, who doth tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend,</l>
                     <l>And paſs all underſtanding, comprehend.</l>
                     <l>Their Joy that's full of glory, who is able</l>
                     <l>To expreſs? for it is unexpreſſable.</l>
                     <l>Chriſt calleth on thee, Sinner, to repent,</l>
                     <l>And he exalted is for this intent,</l>
                     <l>To give repentance and remiſſion.</l>
                     <l>Imploy him to remove thy heart of ſtone.</l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:150340:20"/>
                     <l>They who are turn'd from ſin to God by grace,</l>
                     <l>Find Wiſdom's paths both pleaſantneſs and peace.</l>
                     <l>The Word, the Sacraments, Prayers, and Praiſe,</l>
                     <l>Are lightſome, pleaſant, and delightſome ways.</l>
                     <l>Bleſſed is he who knows the joyful ſound,</l>
                     <l>And who can ſay, O Lord, thy words were found:</l>
                     <l>I did them eat, and thy word was to me</l>
                     <l>My heart's delight, and joyful melody,</l>
                     <l>Admire the Lord's low condeſcendency,</l>
                     <l>That he would ſpeak and write to ſuch as we,</l>
                     <l>And write ſo plainly, that each hungry one,</l>
                     <l>Tho ſimple, findeth food to live upon;</l>
                     <l>And ſo ſublimely, that the Learned might</l>
                     <l>Not nauſeate, but ſearch, deſire, delight;</l>
                     <l>And in ſuch uſeful, ſweet variety,</l>
                     <l>For to prevent loathing ſatiety.</l>
                     <l>Here Hiſtories of grace, and ancient things,</l>
                     <l>Of perſons good and great, of Saints and Kings,</l>
                     <l>Examples rare of Faith and Self-denial,</l>
                     <l>Of patience under the fiery Trial:</l>
                     <l>Of hope when Senſe ſpoke nothing but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair,</l>
                     <l>Of Love, over-coming ill with good, O rare,</l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:150340:20"/>
                     <l>Of Fortitude join'd with a broken Sp'rit,</l>
                     <l>Of warlike courage in a heart contrite,</l>
                     <l>And wit to rule an Army and a Nation,</l>
                     <l>With wiſdom that made wiſe unto ſalvation.</l>
                     <l>But O! the Hiſtory of Hiſtories,</l>
                     <l>So full of Miracles and Myſteries;</l>
                     <l>The Son of God his Incarnation,</l>
                     <l>His coming with life and ſalvation.</l>
                     <l>Theſe good news are, and will be ever freſh,</l>
                     <l>That God was manifeſted in the fleſh,</l>
                     <l>And dwelt with us; then on the Croſs did die,</l>
                     <l>Roſe from the Grave, aſcended up on high.</l>
                     <l>Much may be ſeen of God in the Creation,</l>
                     <l>But he's more clearly ſeen in man's ſalvation:</l>
                     <l>For here appears God's wiſdom manifold,</l>
                     <l>His ſpotleſs Juſtice doth it ſelf unfold,</l>
                     <l>Suing the guiltleſs Surety till he died,</l>
                     <l>Not quitting him till he had ſatisfied.</l>
                     <l>Here Love ſhines bright, as in its proper place,</l>
                     <l>Upon the Mercy-ſeat, the Throne of Grace.</l>
                     <l>Lo, this is love, God who is Love, did give</l>
                     <l>His Son to death, that Enemies might live:</l>
                     <l>His own beloved, loving, lovely Son,</l>
                     <l>Only begotten, with his Father one</l>
                     <l>In Eſſence, one in Mind, and one in Will,</l>
                     <l>who all his Father's Precepts did fulfil,</l>
                     <l>Who holy, harmleſs, ſpotleſs was, yet he</l>
                     <l>Got a command for the loſt ſheep to die:</l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:150340:21"/>
                     <l>To die both in their ſtead, and for their good</l>
                     <l>To waſh away their ſins with his own blood.</l>
                     <l>Chriſt lov'd the Father, and he lov'd the ſheep,</l>
                     <l>And ſo took pleaſure this command to keep.</l>
                     <l>O matchleſs love! it paſſeth all degree;</l>
                     <l>The Judge doth for the Malefactors die.</l>
                     <l>It was his meat to do his Father's will,</l>
                     <l>His work to finiſh, Righteouſneſs fulfil:</l>
                     <l>He went from place to place, ſtill doing good,</l>
                     <l>Healing the ſick, giving the hungry food;</l>
                     <l>Delivering from all maladies and evils,</l>
                     <l>Relieving them who were oppreſt with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils.</l>
                     <l>He was moſt meek, lowly in heart and mind,</l>
                     <l>Moſt merciful, moſt affable and kind.</l>
                     <l>Eaſie he was to be intreated, all</l>
                     <l>Who call'd him, found him ready on a call.</l>
                     <l>When called to a Marriage, he went,</l>
                     <l>And made their water wine, when wine was ſpent:</l>
                     <l>When call'd, he went with <hi>Publicans</hi> and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</l>
                     <l>And even with <hi>Phariſees</hi> unto their Dinners.</l>
                     <l>All who did come for good, got all they ſought,</l>
                     <l>And often better than they askt or thought.</l>
                     <l>The man ſick of the <hi>Palſie,</hi> laid before</l>
                     <l>Chriſt on a bed, ſeeks health, Chriſt giveth more:</l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:150340:21"/>
                     <l>He firſt forgiveth his Iniquity,</l>
                     <l>Then cures his body of its malady.</l>
                     <l>To teach the ſick to ſeek more earneſtly</l>
                     <l>To be from ſin, than from their ſickneſs free.</l>
                     <l>Chriſt ſees a Widow following the Bier</l>
                     <l>Of her dead only Son; he draweth near,</l>
                     <l>And on the Widow hath compaſſion,</l>
                     <l>Reſtores to her alive her only Son.</l>
                     <l>Thus he prevents her expectation</l>
                     <l>With unexpected conſolation.</l>
                     <l>His piercing eye is ſharp to ſee, to ſee</l>
                     <l>His <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s affliction; his eye</l>
                     <l>Affects his tender heart with feeling ſtounds,</l>
                     <l>And all his bowels mercies, mercies ſounds.</l>
                     <l>He quickly comes with all convenient ſpeed,</l>
                     <l>And helps and ſuccours in the time of need,</l>
                     <l>In Chriſt all perſons of each rank and ſtation,</l>
                     <l>May ſee a pattern for their imitation.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Church-Members, learn of him to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</l>
                     <l>God's Servants, and each holy Ordinance.</l>
                     <l>Jeſus when eight days old was circumcis'd:</l>
                     <l>He heard <hi>John</hi> preach, would be by him bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd.</l>
                     <l>He loved Church-communion; for he</l>
                     <l>When others were baptiz'd, baptiz'd would be</l>
                     <l>He kept the Paſſover, and after that</l>
                     <l>His own Supper he himſelf did eat.</l>
                     <l>He ſought and took each fit occaſion</l>
                     <l>For ſpiritual communication,</l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:150340:22"/>
                     <l>And did from earthly things occaſion take</l>
                     <l>Of divine heavenly purpoſes to ſpeak.</l>
                     <l>Vile men things holy wreſt to vile abuſe,</l>
                     <l>He ſinful things drew to an holy uſe:</l>
                     <l>He pray'd with others, taught them what to ſay,</l>
                     <l>And in what order they to God ſhould pray.</l>
                     <l>To pray that God's Name may be hallowed,</l>
                     <l>His kingdom come, his will accompliſhed</l>
                     <l>In Earth, as it's in Heaven; then he allows</l>
                     <l>To ſeek for bread, not things ſuperfluous;</l>
                     <l>And to ſeek more for liberation</l>
                     <l>From ſin and ſnares, than from affliction.</l>
                     <l>Our hearts, when we begin our prayers to raiſe</l>
                     <l>To God in Heaven, and end them in praiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Paſtors, from the great Paſtor learn to preach,</l>
                     <l>Who truth with all authority did teach.</l>
                     <l>His words were right words, plain, and words of grace,</l>
                     <l>Sweet, ſharp, and ſuited to his hearers caſe.</l>
                     <l>He ſmote proud Hypocrites with Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darts:</l>
                     <l>He pour'd the Oil of Joy in broken hearts,</l>
                     <l>And as a Hen her brood under her wings</l>
                     <l>Gathers, ſo would he gather wandring things:</l>
                     <l>He call'd, and preſt his hearers to repent,</l>
                     <l>And to believe on him whom God had ſent.</l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:150340:22"/>
                     <l>On fools, who to believe, of heart were ſlow,</l>
                     <l>He with much patience did great pains be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow:</l>
                     <l>In prayer he prais'd their knowledge, tho but weak,</l>
                     <l>And of their little Faith right much did make.</l>
                     <l>He wept o're thoſe who from him turn'd away,</l>
                     <l>And would not know, nor ponder in their day</l>
                     <l>The things which did belong unto their peace,</l>
                     <l>While they were viſited with Goſpel-grace.</l>
                     <l>And by their ſlighting of Chriſt's Viſitation,</l>
                     <l>Brought on themſelves ruine and deſolation.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To Chriſt let Children, Servants, Subjects look,</l>
                     <l>How pleaſantly he bare Subjections Yoak.</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Joſeph</hi> and his Mother due reſpect</l>
                     <l>He gave, and did himſelf to them ſubject.</l>
                     <l>He payed Tribute; he would not offend:</l>
                     <l>And in his Doctrine he did recommend,</l>
                     <l>To give to <hi>Caeſar</hi> what to him belong'd.</l>
                     <l>He was moſt patient when by Rulers wrong'd.</l>
                     <l>He ſerved Rulers, yea, he thought it meet</l>
                     <l>To ſerve his ſervants, and to waſh their feet.</l>
                     <l>Let all whom the moſt High hath ſet above,</l>
                     <l>Their Fellow-Creatures learn of Chriſt to love,</l>
                     <l>And condeſcend to thoſe of low degree.</l>
                     <l>This lowly love adorns Authority.</l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:150340:23"/>
                     <l>Meekneſs and Mercy, Lowlineſs in Chriſt,</l>
                     <l>With Majeſty and Juſtice well conſiſt,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe of Truth, Meekneſs and Juſtice, he</l>
                     <l>Rides proſperouſly in ſtately Majeſty.</l>
                     <l>He glorieth in goodneſs, mercy, grace,</l>
                     <l>His kingdom ſtands in righteouſneſs and peace,</l>
                     <l>And Joy ſpiritual. O! happy they</l>
                     <l>Who learn of Chriſt to rule, and to obey.</l>
                     <l>Learn of Chriſt to ſuffer, and to die;</l>
                     <l>He had his ſufferings often in his eye,</l>
                     <l>And to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did ſet his face,</l>
                     <l>Went foremoſt in a more than uſual pace:</l>
                     <l>Went to the Garden which his Foes did know,</l>
                     <l>And when they came, himſelf to them did ſhow.</l>
                     <l>He did meet Death before his ſtrength was loſt,</l>
                     <l>He cried loud when he gave up the Ghoſt.</l>
                     <l>He from his Father's Hand the bitter Cup</l>
                     <l>Receiv'd moſt pleaſantly, and drank it up.</l>
                     <l>Pure Nature hath a ſinleſs averſation</l>
                     <l>From wrath and death, and loves ſelf-preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation:</l>
                     <l>So that it cannot chuſe but fear and ſhrink,</l>
                     <l>When ſin-revenging wrath doth mix the drink.</l>
                     <l>This Humane harmleſs will Chriſt giveth up</l>
                     <l>Unto his Father's will, and drinks the Cup,</l>
                     <l>Freely ſubmits his inclination,</l>
                     <l>And ſays, <hi>Lord, not my will, but thine be done.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:150340:23"/>
                     <l>With fervent cries, and tender tears he pray'th,</l>
                     <l>And multiplies the acts of Love and Faith.</l>
                     <l>For <hi>my God, my God, Abba Father,</hi> prove</l>
                     <l>The ſtrength of Faith, and fervency of Love.</l>
                     <l>When that the Sword through his pure Soul was thruſt,</l>
                     <l>He did his Spirit to his Father truft,</l>
                     <l>And to the hand which did him bruiſe and ſmite,</l>
                     <l>In Faith and Love he did his Sp'rit commit.</l>
                     <l>And as his love was wonderful to men</l>
                     <l>At all times, ſo it was moſt wondrous then,</l>
                     <l>When ſorrows fill'd, and did his ſoul ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>round,</l>
                     <l>His kindneſs and compaſſion did abound.</l>
                     <l>Tho he fore-ſaw his torment and reproach,</l>
                     <l>And ſaw the Prince of this World make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach,</l>
                     <l>And found his ſoul with trouble ſo much preſt,</l>
                     <l>That its grief could not be by words expreſt,</l>
                     <l>Yet none of theſe his loving heart diverts</l>
                     <l>From comforting his ſad Diſciples hearts.</l>
                     <l>Before the Paſſover, when Jeſus ſaw</l>
                     <l>His hour was come, and that he ſhould with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw</l>
                     <l>From this world to the Father, having lov'd</l>
                     <l>His own, t'ward the world he conſtant prov'd,</l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:150340:24"/>
                     <l>Lov'd them unto the end. Since now he went</l>
                     <l>To God, from whom he came, his love muſt vent.</l>
                     <l>Like a kind Friend, who from his Friends muſt part,</l>
                     <l>In his farewel pours out his loving heart.</l>
                     <l>In words and deeds, and ſufferings, O! how</l>
                     <l>His love burſts out, and doth all bands o're-flow.</l>
                     <l>He girds himſelf to be for ſervice meet,</l>
                     <l>He ſtands, ſtoops, waſhes, wipes his ſervants feet,</l>
                     <l>To teach them not to lord it, as above</l>
                     <l>Their fellow-ſervants, but to ſerve in love.</l>
                     <l>The Paſſover he did moſt heartily</l>
                     <l>Deſire to eat with them e're he did die.</l>
                     <l>The Paſchal-Lamb ſlain, roaſted which they eat,</l>
                     <l>Meant Chriſt ſlain, ſcorch't in Wrath's juſt burning heat.</l>
                     <l>But Chriſt, Death, Pains, Agony, Sweat of blood,</l>
                     <l>Lov'd as they were our life, eaſe, peace and food.</l>
                     <l>He ſtraitned was till all was finiſhed,</l>
                     <l>And his blood-baptiſm accompliſhed.</l>
                     <l>Behold! again his love will repreſent</l>
                     <l>His death our life, in a new Sacrament.</l>
                     <l>Two feaſts, one end; O rare! in ſuch a night</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n which he was betray'd, to take delight</l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:150340:24"/>
                     <l>To act his own ſad death once and again,</l>
                     <l>A death in which blood, ſhame, and lingring pain:</l>
                     <l>And which was worſt of all, a Curſe did meet,</l>
                     <l>To make his terror every way compleat.</l>
                     <l>He ante-dates his death for their behoof,</l>
                     <l>Turns his ſad death in a ſweet feaſt of love.</l>
                     <l>He gives his broken body for their food,</l>
                     <l>And for their drink he gives his precious blood.</l>
                     <l>The Sword of Juſtice againſt him awoke,</l>
                     <l>It ſtroke him, broke him, he did bear the ſtroak.</l>
                     <l>The Shepherd bore it, who God's equal is,</l>
                     <l>That the poor little ones the ſtroak might miſs.</l>
                     <l>His body broken for them in their ſtead,</l>
                     <l>Is life-procuring, and life-giving bread.</l>
                     <l>The Sword of Juſtice, the blood-thirſty blade</l>
                     <l>Purſues; for blood reſts not till blood be ſhed.</l>
                     <l>The blood of beaſts cannot God's wrath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe,</l>
                     <l>Nor purge the Conſcience, nor give it eaſe.</l>
                     <l>Vile finite man could never ſatisfie</l>
                     <l>For ſin againſt God infinite, tho he</l>
                     <l>Should bleed for ever in this helpleſs caſe.</l>
                     <l>Chriſt cometh in for his poor ſheep's releaſe.</l>
                     <l>He ſaith, <hi>I come, I come; behold and ſee,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As in the book it written is of me;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:150340:25"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A Body, Lord, thou haſt for me prepar'd:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Draw blood of me, and let the ſheep be ſpar'd.</l>
                     <l>I do delight even my hearts blood to ſhed</l>
                     <l>For them, that their ſin may be pardoned.</l>
                     <l>Come all ye whom the fiery law doth charge</l>
                     <l>With guilt and wrath, and who your hearts enlarge</l>
                     <l>For righteouſneſs, and who for pardon pant,</l>
                     <l>Come, drink the blood of the new covenant.</l>
                     <l>This drink will quench thy thirſt, and ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heat,</l>
                     <l>Which guilt and wrath do in thy ſoul beget.</l>
                     <l>Chriſt gives himſelf for food, to intimate,</l>
                     <l>That he himſelf is ours, in us, and that</l>
                     <l>He is one with us by a lively union,</l>
                     <l>And that our life conſiſteth in communion</l>
                     <l>With him, who gives us life, and growth, and ſtrength,</l>
                     <l>And perfects what concerneth us at length.</l>
                     <l>This puts his loving kindneſs out of doubt,</l>
                     <l>That he comes in, and will not ſtand without;</l>
                     <l>And comes in, that he with his Friends may feaſt,</l>
                     <l>And gives himſelf for food to every gueſt:</l>
                     <l>He gives his fleſh for bread, and to make up</l>
                     <l>The feaſt, he pours his blood into the Cup.</l>
                     <l>White others have but Bread and Wine for food,</l>
                     <l>Believers eat Chriſt's Body, drink his Blood.</l>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:150340:25"/>
                     <l>He will not live without them, he doth give</l>
                     <l>Life unto them, and Chriſt in them doth live.</l>
                     <l>Yea, the life which they in the fleſh do live,</l>
                     <l>They live it as they on the Son believe.</l>
                     <l>Behold again his Love, behold him die,</l>
                     <l>Behold him leave his little ones a legacy,</l>
                     <l>In a moſt ſure, well order'd Teſtament,</l>
                     <l>And gives it ſealed by a Sacrament,</l>
                     <l>This Teſtament containeth all that's good,</l>
                     <l>All that is purchaſed by Jeſus blood:</l>
                     <l>It cannot changed be, it muſt endure;</l>
                     <l>The great Teſtator's death doth make it ſure</l>
                     <l>He dies to ratifie his latter Will,</l>
                     <l>He lives Executor, it to fulfil:</l>
                     <l>He gave himſelf for them, to them he gives</l>
                     <l>Himſelf; for them he dies, for them he lives.</l>
                     <l>Yet ſtill here's more of love, the loving art.</l>
                     <l>Is learned beſt from Chriſt's moſt loving heart:</l>
                     <l>He leaves a token of his love moſt kind,</l>
                     <l>To keep him: and his death ſtill in their mind.</l>
                     <l>A token which he will have to remain</l>
                     <l>With them, until he come from Heaven again.</l>
                     <l>He ſays, <hi>This is my body for you broken,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Take this, as of my love a ſign and token:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Take, eat, and when this braken bread you ſee,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And take and eat it, then remember me.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And drink this Cup, and drink ye of it all:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As often as this Bread and Cup ye ſhall</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:150340:26"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Eat and drink, ye ſhew forth, and do record</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The bloody breaking death of Chriſt the Lord.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Since theſe Love tokens are moſt excellent,</l>
                     <l>Which do to us moſt clearly repreſent</l>
                     <l>An abſent friend, to ſhew what he hath done</l>
                     <l>For us, what hardſhips for us undergone:</l>
                     <l>And thoſe moſt charming and endearing prove,</l>
                     <l>Which repreſent his lovelineſs and love.</l>
                     <l>This Sacrament is an illuſtrious</l>
                     <l>Symbol of love, preſenting Chriſt to us,</l>
                     <l>As broken, bleeding, dying in our ſtead,</l>
                     <l>Broken, that he might unto us be bread;</l>
                     <l>Bleeding, that he might us with drink relieve,</l>
                     <l>And dying, that we by his death might live.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>His Farewell Sermon, regiſter'd by <hi>John,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is full of love and conſolation,</l>
                     <l>Where you will find moſt kindly compellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</l>
                     <l>Comforting Truths, ſtrengthening Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</l>
                     <l>And promiſes moſt great and precious,</l>
                     <l>Moſt fit for them, moſt ſweet and gracious.</l>
                     <l>His Sermon ſweet, in a ſweet Prayer ends,</l>
                     <l>Where he them to his Father recommends;</l>
                     <l>And prays for all that ſhould believe upon</l>
                     <l>His Name, through the Word, that ye might be one,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As thou</hi> (ſays he) <hi>O Father, art in me,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And I in thee, they one in us may be.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:150340:26"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I will that they whom thou haſt given me,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Be with me, that they may my Glory ſee.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I have declared unto them thy Name,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And will continue to declare the ſame,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That the love wherewith thou haſt loved me,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>May be in them, and I in them might be.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Himſelf, his Glory, and his Father's love</l>
                     <l>To him, he gives to them; and this doth prove,</l>
                     <l>He will no good deny, but all impart</l>
                     <l>Unto his Spouſe, who raviſheth his heart.</l>
                     <l>For her his hands, feet, ſide, and heart did bleed:</l>
                     <l>Theſe ſtreams did from the Spring of Love proceed.</l>
                     <l>His bleeding hands, feet, ſide, and heart, do prove,</l>
                     <l>That our Lord Jeſus Chriſt did die for love.</l>
                     <l>In ſuffering, he acted, finiſhed</l>
                     <l>His work, his Father's will accompliſhed;</l>
                     <l>Payed the price, Juſtice to ſatisfie,</l>
                     <l>His Priſoners to ranſom and ſet free.</l>
                     <l>And when he ignominiouſly did die,</l>
                     <l>His Foes he vanquiſhed moſt gloriouſly.</l>
                     <l>Heroick Facts, which Hiſtories record,</l>
                     <l>Are nothing to the acts of Chriſt the Lord,</l>
                     <l>Who the Red Dragons, the old Serpent's head</l>
                     <l>Bruiſed, and all Hell's Powers vanquiſhed;</l>
                     <l>Deſtroyed Death, and took away its ſting,</l>
                     <l>And rend'red it, tho grim, a harmleſs thing;</l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:150340:27"/>
                     <l>O'recame the world, and made an end of ſin,</l>
                     <l>And everlaſting righteouſneſs brought in.</l>
                     <l>To God he Glory gave, to Earth brought Peace,</l>
                     <l>And towards worthleſs men good will and grace.</l>
                     <l>The feigned Loves which are in forg'd Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances,</l>
                     <l>Tho they be ſtrain'd, are dull and cloudy Fancies,</l>
                     <l>And nothing to his matchleſs wondrous love,</l>
                     <l>Which is all finite minds and thoughts above,</l>
                     <l>The Spirit did the Goſpel oft indite,</l>
                     <l>And moved four Evangeliſts to write,</l>
                     <l>That we might often read, and hear, and ſee</l>
                     <l>Of godlineſs the true great myſtery;</l>
                     <l>That in beholding we might be transform'd</l>
                     <l>Into Chriſt's Image, and to him conform'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If thou take pleaſure to read Propheſies,</l>
                     <l>Again into the Scripture turn thine eyes,</l>
                     <l>Where thou wilt find, that in the days of old</l>
                     <l>Things future were long e're they came fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told,</l>
                     <l>The Promiſes of Chriſt are there moſt clear,</l>
                     <l>And were fulfilled when he did appear.</l>
                     <l>They who had eyes to ſee, could not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake</l>
                     <l>Him, of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets ſpake.</l>
                     <l>All circumſtances here did meet and twift,</l>
                     <l>What they foretold fulfilled was in Chriſt.</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:150340:27"/>
                     <l>The Promiſes ſo great and precious</l>
                     <l>Aſſures us, that the Lord is gracious.</l>
                     <l>His Word and Oath, which ever do endure,</l>
                     <l>Do make his mercies to his people ſure.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>May worthleſs I theſe Promiſes embrace?</l>
                     <l>Thou maiſt, for they are Promiſes of Grace.</l>
                     <l>If thou be miſerable and impure,</l>
                     <l>They promiſe cleanſing, they are mercies ſure.</l>
                     <l>As cleanſing purgeth from impurity,</l>
                     <l>So mercy pities, ſaves from miſery.</l>
                     <l>If thou do thirſt and hunger after all</l>
                     <l>The Promiſes, thine own thou maiſt them call.</l>
                     <l>The needy ſoul that longs for righteouſneſs,</l>
                     <l>May claim the Promiſe, fulneſs bleſſedneſs.</l>
                     <l>Since Chriſt hath bleſt the hungry thirſty foul,</l>
                     <l>Such ſure are bleſt, none can his Word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul.</l>
                     <l>Once cloſe with Chriſt, all Promiſes are then</l>
                     <l>Thine; for in him they are, <hi>Yea and Amen.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If thou embrace all his Commands aright,</l>
                     <l>Thou maiſt in all his Promiſes delight.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Would you read laws, in Scripture you may ſee</l>
                     <l>The laws of God moſt holy and moſt high,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Will's the rule of all holineſs,</l>
                     <l>Of love and mercy, and of righteouſneſs.</l>
                     <l>Theſe pure commands light to the eyes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part:</l>
                     <l>They'r right and good, and do rejoice the heart.</l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:150340:28"/>
                     <l>Receive them in thy mind, ſince they are light:</l>
                     <l>And ſince they'r good, make them thy hearts delight.</l>
                     <l>Great peace have they, O Lord, thy law that love</l>
                     <l>Nothing to them a ſtumbling-block ſhall prove.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Would you read Proverbs, much ſence in few words,</l>
                     <l>The Scripture Proverbs plenteouſly affords.</l>
                     <l>In Scripture rare Epiſtles you will find,</l>
                     <l>Where to his Friends Chriſt writes his heart and mind:</l>
                     <l>And as their caſe requires, ſo he in love</l>
                     <l>Sometimes commends, and ſometimes doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Would you read news, here's news both great and true,</l>
                     <l>Good tidings of great Joy, and ever new,</l>
                     <l>That God was manifeſt in humane fleſh,</l>
                     <l>Will be for ever wondrous news and freſh.</l>
                     <l>He is the ſame to day, and yeſterday,</l>
                     <l>And is the ſame for ever and for aye.</l>
                     <l>His love's the ſame, it never waxeth old,</l>
                     <l>His blood's ſtill freſh, his vertue grows not cold,</l>
                     <l>He's white and ruddy ſtill, his beauty rare</l>
                     <l>Doth never fade, no age can it impair;</l>
                     <l>His locks are black, no grey hairs there are ſeen,</l>
                     <l>His Marriage bed continues ever green.</l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:150340:28"/>
                     <l>All earthly things do languiſh and decay;</l>
                     <l>The faſhion of the world doth paſs away.</l>
                     <l>Theſe things are nothing elſe but ſhadows flee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</l>
                     <l>Which ſeem to be, and have no ſolid being:</l>
                     <l>But Chriſt is truth, and new creatures true,</l>
                     <l>Old things are paſt, lo all things here are new.</l>
                     <l>Theſe things fade not with time, they grow not frail,</l>
                     <l>They are eternal and ſhall never fail.</l>
                     <l>New creatures wax not old, they never die;</l>
                     <l>Newneſs of life laſts to eternity.</l>
                     <l>New are their hearts, their ſpirits, minds and ſenſe,</l>
                     <l>Their acts are acts of new obedience;</l>
                     <l>Their way is new, as light it ſhines alway,</l>
                     <l>Still more and more unto the perfect day.</l>
                     <l>Theſe creatures new have a new ſecret name,</l>
                     <l>And a new City, <hi>New Jeruſalem;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A new Heav'n and new Earth, which far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</l>
                     <l>This World; for there all righteouſneſs doth dwell.</l>
                     <l>New various fruits they gather from the tree</l>
                     <l>Of Life, and drink new wine perpetually;</l>
                     <l>Eternal draughts of Light, Love and Joy,</l>
                     <l>While God himſelf they fully do enjoy.</l>
                     <l>Ah Fools! who ſeek for needleſs Novelties,</l>
                     <l>To feed fantaſtick Curioſities,</l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:150340:29"/>
                     <l>Of precious time ſo prodigally loſt,</l>
                     <l>Your brave new nothings will not quit the coſt.</l>
                     <l>Search for the new things that are great and true,</l>
                     <l>And of this labour thou ſhalt never rue.</l>
                     <l>Theſe news thy ſoul to wondering will raiſe,</l>
                     <l>And yield ſweet matter of new Songs of praiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Art thou diſpos'd to ſing? apply thine ear,</l>
                     <l>In ſcripture thou a joyful ſound ſhalt hear</l>
                     <l>Of Pſalms, and Hymns, and Songs Spiritual,</l>
                     <l>Which make a melody celeſtial.</l>
                     <l>No Poet now can ſuch Compoſures write;</l>
                     <l>For the great Maker did theſe Songs indite:</l>
                     <l>They came from Heaven, and by a heavenly ſtrain,</l>
                     <l>They lift the ſoul from Earth to Heaven again.</l>
                     <l>There are high Songs made touching the great King,</l>
                     <l>Who hath pre-eminence in every thing:</l>
                     <l>There are moſt ſtately Songs of acts divine,</l>
                     <l>Sweet Songs of Love, which better are than wine.</l>
                     <l>Here mournful Songs, and Songs of joy and gladneſs,</l>
                     <l>And here are Songs compos'd of mirth and ſadneſs.</l>
                     <l>The Pſalm begins ſometimes with ſighs and tears,</l>
                     <l>And ſad complaints of dangers and of fears;</l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:150340:29"/>
                     <l>But while the Pſalmiſt ſings, the grief and fray</l>
                     <l>Evaniſh, and are ſweetly ſung away.</l>
                     <l>Theſe fingers travel much aloft, to raiſe</l>
                     <l>Their hearts and tongues to higheſt Notes of praiſe:</l>
                     <l>They call for help, invite the creatures all</l>
                     <l>In Earth, Seas, Air, the Hoſts celeſtial.</l>
                     <l>But all the praiſe that creatures can afford,</l>
                     <l>Is far below the praiſe due to the Lord.</l>
                     <l>This rent will never fully payed be,</l>
                     <l>Through all the Ages of Eternity:</l>
                     <l>But they who ever praiſe, are ever bleſt,</l>
                     <l>In reſtleſs praiſe there is eternal reſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Unto the word the Lord ſubjoined hath</l>
                     <l>The Sacraments, for to confirm our Faith,</l>
                     <l>That as we hear, ſo we may clearly ſee</l>
                     <l>Chriſt and his Grace preſented to our eye.</l>
                     <l>In Baptiſm, behold, Chriſt doth apply</l>
                     <l>His Blood and Spirit us to purifie,</l>
                     <l>To purge away our guilt and filthineſs,</l>
                     <l>To give us holineſs and righteouſneſs.</l>
                     <l>Be pure and clean, and of a holy frame,</l>
                     <l>Since thou waſt waſhed in God's holy Name.</l>
                     <l>Unto the holy One, the holy Three,</l>
                     <l>Thou offer'd waſt, ſhould'ſt thou not holy be?</l>
                     <l>Think never ſhame holineſs to avow,</l>
                     <l>Glory to ſtand to thy Baptiſmal Vow.</l>
                     <l>Abhor the filthy luſts of Swiniſh Hogs,</l>
                     <l>Diſdain to caſt what's holy unto Dogs:</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:150340:30"/>
                     <l>Watch, fight againſt all worldly luſts and evils,</l>
                     <l>Reſiſt unclean, lying and murthering Devils:</l>
                     <l>Be ſtrong in God, and in his power of might,</l>
                     <l>The War is holy, and the Cauſe is right:</l>
                     <l>Put on Gods armour, ſtand, ſtand, do not flee,</l>
                     <l>Upon the Captain always fix thine eye.</l>
                     <l>He is the Captain of Salvation,</l>
                     <l>Cleave unto him, and thou ſhalt ſurely win;</l>
                     <l>For he hath given to all thy Foes the foil,</l>
                     <l>Come after him, and gather up the ſpoil:</l>
                     <l>He will thee feaſt in midſt of all thy fight,</l>
                     <l>Cover thy Table in thine Enemies ſight.</l>
                     <l>A Banquet in the fight expect thou may,</l>
                     <l>Since Chriſt Love's Banner doth o're thee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play.</l>
                     <l>O! let it not be ever ſaid of thee,</l>
                     <l>That from Chriſt's Colours thou away did flee.</l>
                     <l>Chriſt and his fulneſs in the union-feaſt,</l>
                     <l>We may both hear, and ſee, ſmell, touch, and taſte.</l>
                     <l>By theſe ſame ports were Satan, Death, and Sin,</l>
                     <l>Enter'd, Chriſt, Life and Righteouſneſs, come in.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Adam</hi> did hear, take, ſmell, touch, taſte t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> fruit,</l>
                     <l>And was transform'd to a vile mortal Brute.</l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:150340:30"/>
                     <l>He is the Living, the Life-giving Bread,</l>
                     <l>Here is the meat indeed the drink indeed,</l>
                     <l>Under the ſhadow of this true Apple tree,</l>
                     <l>Sit down, it's Fruit to thy taſte ſweet ſhall be.</l>
                     <l>This tree of life, this true and noble Vine</l>
                     <l>Yields Grapes, which bleed true life, a life di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</l>
                     <l>Chriſt would be broken, that he might be bread,</l>
                     <l>And that the dead might live, he would be dead.</l>
                     <l>He would bleed out his life, that we might drink</l>
                     <l>Life in his blood, remember him, and think</l>
                     <l>Still of his Death, and in his Temple ſtill</l>
                     <l>Think of his Love, and of his latter Will.</l>
                     <l>Thou who art willing Chriſt himſelf to take,</l>
                     <l>And all his fulneſs, no more ſcruples make;</l>
                     <l>For as the bread thou eat'ſt, and as the wine</l>
                     <l>Thou drink'ſt, belongs to thee, ſo Chriſt is thine.</l>
                     <l>As food the empty body ſatiates,</l>
                     <l>And life and ſtrength recruits and recreates;</l>
                     <l>So Chriſt to ſouls doth full contentment give:</l>
                     <l>He is their ſtrength and life, by which they live.</l>
                     <l>If he dwell in thee, thou ſhalt filled be</l>
                     <l>With all Gods fullneſs moſt abundantly,</l>
                     <l>And thou ſhalt live, not thou, but rather he,</l>
                     <l>Who is a quickning Spirit, ſhall live in thee.</l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:150340:31"/>
                     <l>Faint not when to great works thou haſt a call;</l>
                     <l>In Chriſt, who ſtrengthens thee, thou maiſt do all.</l>
                     <l>Thou wilt him find life giving, ſtrenthening food,</l>
                     <l>The living Spring of all that's truly good.</l>
                     <l>Prepare thy ſelf for this great holy Feaſt,</l>
                     <l>The King himſelf obſerveth every gueſt:</l>
                     <l>He who had not his Wedding-garment on,</l>
                     <l>Incurr'd the Sentence of Damnation.</l>
                     <l>If thou come thither as to common food,</l>
                     <l>Thou wilt draw on the guilt of Jeſu's blood.</l>
                     <l>Come with repentance, mourn when thou doſt ſee</l>
                     <l>The Lord, whom thou by ſin didſt crucifie.</l>
                     <l>Come hungring, thirſting for this holy Feaſt,</l>
                     <l>The hungring ſoul ſhall be with goodneſs bleſt:</l>
                     <l>Come meek and lowly to Chriſt crucified,</l>
                     <l>The meek ſhall eat, and ſhall be ſatisfied:</l>
                     <l>Chriſt dwells with thoſe who are of humble Spirit,</l>
                     <l>And doth revive the heart of the contrite.</l>
                     <l>Thou muſt have Faith, that Chriſt himſelf thou may</l>
                     <l>Eat Spiritually, not in a carnal way.</l>
                     <l>Purge out the leaven of hypocriſie,</l>
                     <l>And eat this feaſt with heart-ſincerity:</l>
                     <l>Purge malice out, Diviſion detaſte,</l>
                     <l>This is a Love, and a Communion-feaſt.</l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:150340:31"/>
                     <l>Forgive the ſins of others heartily,</l>
                     <l>As God, for Chriſt's ſake, hath forgiven thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If wants diſcourage, guilt ſtare in thy face,</l>
                     <l>Then judge thy ſelf, beg mercy, ſeek for grace.</l>
                     <l>If thou ſeek Jeſus, fear not, do not ſtay,</l>
                     <l>He hath all that thou want'ſt, haſte, come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way:</l>
                     <l>Come to the blood of ſprinkling with thy ſin,</l>
                     <l>The Fountain's open, waſh thy ſelf therein.</l>
                     <l>As it's of grace that the moſt glorious Lord</l>
                     <l>Speaks unto us, and ſeals his faithful Word</l>
                     <l>By Sacraments; ſo it is of his grace,</l>
                     <l>That we may ſpeak to him in every place:</l>
                     <l>Yea, he moſt graciouſly of us requires,</l>
                     <l>That we in every thing make our deſires</l>
                     <l>Known t' him by prayer and ſupplication,</l>
                     <l>That we may freed be of all vexation,</l>
                     <l>And that we may to our comfort find,</l>
                     <l>The peace of God guarding our heart and mind.</l>
                     <l>Offer thy hearts deſires unto the Lord,</l>
                     <l>For things agreeable unto his Word:</l>
                     <l>Pray in the Spirit, who helps up every groan,</l>
                     <l>And ſigh and ſuit, we cannot pray alone:</l>
                     <l>Pray in Chriſt's Name, if acceſs thou would'ſt have</l>
                     <l>To grace, and anſwers of thy ſuit receive.</l>
                     <l>This is the new and living way, the gate</l>
                     <l>Of life, that leadeth to the Mercy-ſeat.</l>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:150340:32"/>
                     <l>All thoſe for whom Chriſt doeth interceed,</l>
                     <l>Mercy and grace, find in the time of need.</l>
                     <l>Be humble, fervent, pray in love and faith:</l>
                     <l>Life up pure hands without doubting and wrath:</l>
                     <l>Confeſs thy ſins with ſorrow and with ſhame:</l>
                     <l>For mercies praiſe the Lord's moſt holy Name:</l>
                     <l>And pray that God's Name may be hallowed,</l>
                     <l>Before thou com'ſt to ſeek for daily bread.</l>
                     <l>If anſwers come not ſoon, wait, knock again,</l>
                     <l>He hath not ſaid, <hi>Seek ye my face in vain.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Seek, ask, knock, wait with expectation,</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt rejoice in God's ſalvation.</l>
                     <l>The very pouring out of a ſad heart</l>
                     <l>Before the Lord, will ſomewhat eaſe its ſmart.</l>
                     <l>He heareth prayer, and he loves to hear</l>
                     <l>His Doves, his Turtles voice; he bows his ear.</l>
                     <l>All their deſires, groans, breathings, chatterings,</l>
                     <l>Are pleaſant muſick to the King of Kings:</l>
                     <l>Theſe broken Notes he joins in pleaſant ſets</l>
                     <l>Of Muſick, and their moaning words repeats:</l>
                     <l>He hears <hi>Ephraim,</hi> while he doth bemoan</l>
                     <l>Himſelf; he telleth every word and groan:</l>
                     <l>His bowels move, he hath compaſſion</l>
                     <l>Upon his pleaſant child, and his dear Son.</l>
                     <l>Is it not meet that ſince the Lord takes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</l>
                     <l>To hear, and to repeat thy ſuits takes leaſure,</l>
                     <l>That thou with pleaſure ſhould'ſt perſiſt to cry,</l>
                     <l>And wait his leaſure till he do reply?</l>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:150340:32"/>
                     <l>Sometimes he anſwers Prayers e're they are done;</l>
                     <l>Sometimes he anſwers e're they be begun:</l>
                     <l>For he regardeth our neceſſity,</l>
                     <l>And anſwereth our need before we cry:</l>
                     <l>And ſometimes humble, patient expectation</l>
                     <l>Is a moſt needful part of ſupplication.</l>
                     <l>That man is indiſcreet who is offended,</l>
                     <l>That he's not anſwered ere his ſuit be ended.</l>
                     <l>The needy he will not forget alway:</l>
                     <l>The poor man's hope ſhall not be loſt for ay.</l>
                     <l>Think it not then a wearineſs to pray,</l>
                     <l>To come by this new, true and living way,</l>
                     <l>With boldneſs by the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt,</l>
                     <l>The Son of God, the merciful High-Prieſt,</l>
                     <l>Who doth for ever live to interceed</l>
                     <l>For ſinners ſenſible of ſin and need;</l>
                     <l>And takes thoſe who come to him by the hand,</l>
                     <l>And brings them into grace, wherein they ſtand,</l>
                     <l>Into the holieſt, the Mercy-ſeat,</l>
                     <l>That from the God of Grace they Grace may get;</l>
                     <l>Pardons of ſins, cures of all maladies,</l>
                     <l>And for all wants full ſuitable ſupplies;</l>
                     <l>Light, Life, Strength, Grace to do and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere,</l>
                     <l>When they are tempt with pleaſure or with fear:</l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:150340:33"/>
                     <l>Yea, more than they can ask, or think upon,</l>
                     <l>Grace, Grace, ſure mercies, God's ſalvation.</l>
                     <l>Are not then all God's Ordinances ſweet,</l>
                     <l>Since in them he doth with his people meet?</l>
                     <l>Himſelf, his Mind, his Grace he doth impart</l>
                     <l>To them, and they pour out to him their heart.</l>
                     <l>Bleſſed are they the joyful ſound who hear,</l>
                     <l>And to God's Word apply their heart and ear.</l>
                     <l>It's Spirit and Life; it light in darkneſs gives,</l>
                     <l>And when they faint and fear, it them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves.</l>
                     <l>O! bleſſed are they who are waſhed in</l>
                     <l>The Fountain opened for faults and ſin:</l>
                     <l>Theſe Waters cleanſe, heal, quicken, and make grow</l>
                     <l>All things, where they do come and overflow.</l>
                     <l>And happy are they who by Chriſt, the King,</l>
                     <l>Are brought into the houſe of banquetting:</l>
                     <l>And happy they who by his Sp'rit are led</l>
                     <l>Unto his houſe of Prayer, and there made glad.</l>
                     <l>If this begun-communion be ſo ſweet,</l>
                     <l>What will it be when it's in Heaven compleat?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As for Chriſt's Rod and Croſs, tho they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear</l>
                     <l>So ſharp and ſad, yet follow, do not fear:</l>
                     <l>That he himſelf doth humble to reprove,</l>
                     <l>And chaſten thee, it's condeſcending love:</l>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:150340:33"/>
                     <l>For if thou wert without correction,</l>
                     <l>Thou wouldſt a Baſtard be, and not a Son.</l>
                     <l>It's better to endure Paternal Ire,</l>
                     <l>Than bear the vengeance of eternal fire.</l>
                     <l>If thou receive the rod with ſpirit mild,</l>
                     <l>Thou maiſt be ſure God treats thee as a child.</l>
                     <l>Why ſhouldſt thou his chaſtiſing hand ſuſpect,</l>
                     <l>Since for thy profit he doth thee correct,</l>
                     <l>That we may partake of his holineſs,</l>
                     <l>And may bring forth the fruits of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</l>
                     <l>His fire will not conſume thee, but thy ſin:</l>
                     <l>It purgeth out thy filthy droſs and tin.</l>
                     <l>Theſe Thorns are kindly ſharp, which hedge the way,</l>
                     <l>That thou maiſt not thy lovers find, but ſay,</l>
                     <l>I will to my firſt husband go; I know</l>
                     <l>That it was better then with me than now.</l>
                     <l>He is to anger ſlow, he ſtirs not all</l>
                     <l>His wrath, he quickly lets the quarrel fall:</l>
                     <l>He ſpares even when he ſtrikes, debates in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</l>
                     <l>Waits to be gracious, gives ſpace and leaſure</l>
                     <l>To thoſe whom he chaſtiſeth to repent,</l>
                     <l>Speaks to their heart, to move it to relent:</l>
                     <l>Deſpiſe not the Almighty's chaſtiſement,</l>
                     <l>And when he thee rebuketh, do not faint:</l>
                     <l>Humble thy ſelf under his mighty hand,</l>
                     <l>Obey his will, it's madneſs to withſtand.</l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:150340:34"/>
                     <l>Turn to his hand that ſmites, and kiſs the rod:</l>
                     <l>And it is meet that thus thou ſay to God,</l>
                     <l>I have chaſtiſement born, I'le not offend:</l>
                     <l>Have mercy, give me Grace my faults to mend:</l>
                     <l>What I ſee not, Lord, teach me, that I may</l>
                     <l>Know ſecret ſins, and no more go aſtray.</l>
                     <l>Bleſt is the man who is of God chaſtiſed,</l>
                     <l>And from his Law thus taught and exerciſed.</l>
                     <l>Sin brings down rods, rods bring forth fruits of peace,</l>
                     <l>Chriſt turns the fruits of ſin to means of grace:</l>
                     <l>God's ſoveraign Grace makes changes ſtrange of things:</l>
                     <l>It life from death, ſweet from bitter brings;</l>
                     <l>Peace out of trouble, out of darkneſs light;</l>
                     <l>Out of the Eater meet, from grief delight.</l>
                     <l>What of it ſelf did to deſtruction tend,</l>
                     <l>Grace makes it in ſalvation to end.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As for Chriſt's Croſs, be not at it offended;</l>
                     <l>For it can never be enough commended:</l>
                     <l>O! it's a holy, pleaſant, ſtately thing,</l>
                     <l>To be conform'd to him in ſuffering.</l>
                     <l>Remember oft his oft repeated word,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Servant is not greater than his Lord:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>It is enough, and very fair that he</l>
                     <l>Who's a Diſciple, as his Maſter be.</l>
                     <l>Is thy condition mean? canſt thou not find</l>
                     <l>Accommodation unto thy mind?</l>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:150340:34"/>
                     <l>Haſt thou no harboury, no houſe, nor hold,</l>
                     <l>To ſhelter thee from ſtorms? look and behold,</l>
                     <l>The Firſt-begotten to the world brought in,</l>
                     <l>In an Out-houſe, and not into the Inn.</l>
                     <l>He, unto whom the Angels worſhip paid,</l>
                     <l>Is in a Manger, not a Cradle laid.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Foxes have holes, and each fowl hath its neſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Chriſt had not whereupon his head to rest.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Want'ſt thou wherewith to buy thy daily bread?</l>
                     <l>Some of their ſubſtance to him miniſtred.</l>
                     <l>Or art thou from thy Native Soil exil'd?</l>
                     <l>Chriſt driven was to <hi>Egypt</hi> when a child.</l>
                     <l>Art thou reproached? Vile iniquities</l>
                     <l>Were caſt on him, calumnies and lies;</l>
                     <l>Vile drunkenneſs, ſenſual gluttony,</l>
                     <l>Colluſion with Devils, blaſphemy,</l>
                     <l>Madneſs, deceit, and friendlineſs to vice,</l>
                     <l>And all that crafty malice could deviſe,</l>
                     <l>Was charg'd on him, whom they proclaim'd abroad,</l>
                     <l>An Enemy to <hi>Coeſar</hi> and to God.</l>
                     <l>Do Friends turn Foes, or do they faint and flee</l>
                     <l>From thee in ſtraits? to Jeſus turn thine eye:</l>
                     <l>His own Diſciples did leave him alone:</l>
                     <l>They to their own were ſcattered and gone:</l>
                     <l>He was by <hi>Judas</hi> traiterouſly betrayed,</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Peter</hi> thrice moſt ſhamefully denied.</l>
                     <l>Art thou a Priſoner, and hardly uſed,</l>
                     <l>Purſu'd to death, and ſcornfully abuſed?</l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:150340:35"/>
                     <l>Chriſt as a Thief, was apprehended, bound,</l>
                     <l>As a mock-King in purple cloath'd, and crown'd</l>
                     <l>With pricking Thorns, a Reed put in his hand,</l>
                     <l>As a mock-Scepter; then they do command,</l>
                     <l>That he hood-wink't, ſhould tell who did him ſmite.</l>
                     <l>To ſhew at him as Prophet, their deſpite,</l>
                     <l>They ſpit on him, and ſcourge him cruelly,</l>
                     <l>And lead him out upon a Croſs to die</l>
                     <l>A lingring, ſhameful, painful, curſed death,</l>
                     <l>On which he bore our ſins and divine wrath.</l>
                     <l>Theſe were the weights that did his ſoul di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs:</l>
                     <l>His ſweat was blood, when bruiſed in this preſs.</l>
                     <l>The Croſs, as Chriſt hath left it, we may ſay</l>
                     <l>Is light, Chriſt took its greateſt weight away:</l>
                     <l>He wrath, the bitterneſs of death drunk up,</l>
                     <l>And left no vengeance in his peoples cup:</l>
                     <l>For wrath and death, he love and life puts in,</l>
                     <l>Which <hi>Marab</hi>'s waters make more ſweet than wine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Take up his burden, it is light and meet,</l>
                     <l>And drink his cup, it healthful is and ſweet.</l>
                     <l>To bear about the dying of ſweet-Jeſus</l>
                     <l>Will not us kill, but quicken, ſtrengthen, eaſe us.</l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:150340:35"/>
                     <l>They're highly honoured who ſuffer ſhame</l>
                     <l>For Jeſus ſake, and for his glorious Name:</l>
                     <l>Reproach for Chriſt, is Riches much more great</l>
                     <l>Than <hi>Egypt</hi>'s Pleaſures, Treaſures, Honours, State:</l>
                     <l>Shame for him honour is, and loſs is gain:</l>
                     <l>In death for him is life, and eaſe in pain.</l>
                     <l>When all day long they're killed for his ſake,</l>
                     <l>Like ſheep for ſlaughter, burned at a ſtake</l>
                     <l>They Conquerors, and more than Conquerors prove,</l>
                     <l>Through him who them eternally doth love.</l>
                     <l>Turn thine eyes from the dark ſide of the Croſs,</l>
                     <l>On which appears diſhonour, pain and loſs,</l>
                     <l>And turn upon the lightſome ſide thine eye,</l>
                     <l>Where pleaſure, gain and glory thou maiſt ſee.</l>
                     <l>Chriſt's own Example will us beſt direct,</l>
                     <l>How of the Croſs to take a right proſpect.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Son of man is glorified,</hi> he ſaid,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And God in him is alſo glorified.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If God in him thus glorified be,</l>
                     <l>God ſhall in him himſelf ſtraight glorifie.</l>
                     <l>He Glory ſaw in being crucified,</l>
                     <l>He ſaw God by his ſuffering glorified:</l>
                     <l>He ſaw the heavenly glory to enſue:</l>
                     <l>Keep ſtill this Triple Glory in thy view.</l>
                     <l>Sigh not then at the Croſs, as ſad and ſorry,</l>
                     <l>But ſhout in triumph, Glory, glory, glory.</l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:150340:36"/>
                     <l>Live to God's Glory, for his Glory die,</l>
                     <l>It is thy Glory God to glorifie.</l>
                     <l>If by thy death God glorified be,</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt in Glory live eternally.</l>
                     <l>They who with Chriſt do ſuffer, with him reign,</l>
                     <l>And bearing palms, eternal triumph ſing.</l>
                     <l>If for the Name of Chriſt reproach'd thou be,</l>
                     <l>The Spirit of God and Glory reſts on thee.</l>
                     <l>Theſe momentary croſſes which are light,</l>
                     <l>Work endleſs Glory of exceeding weight.</l>
                     <l>Yet go not from thy way to ſeek a croſs,</l>
                     <l>Follow thy calling, to God's way keep cloſe:</l>
                     <l>That Croſs which thy wiſe Lord for thee thinks meet,</l>
                     <l>Is in thy way, in the great King's High-ſtreet:</l>
                     <l>That thou muſt take it up, or elſe go wrong,</l>
                     <l>Medling in what doth not to thee belong.</l>
                     <l>If in thy ſufferings thou wouldſt have delight,</l>
                     <l>See that thy call be clear, the cauſe be right:</l>
                     <l>Take up thy Croſs in Chriſt's Name, and his ſtrength,</l>
                     <l>That of thy race thou maiſt run all the length.</l>
                     <l>Pray to be ſtrengthen'd by his glorious might,</l>
                     <l>To ſuffer with all patience and delight.</l>
                     <l>Tho thou wert burned, yet if thou haſt not</l>
                     <l>Love, burning will not profit thee a Jot.</l>
                     <l>Unto thy hungry Enemy give food:</l>
                     <l>Love thoſe who hate thee, vanquiſh ill with good:</l>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:150340:36"/>
                     <l>And pray that thoſe who do impoveriſh thee,</l>
                     <l>With the true riches may enriched be:</l>
                     <l>That they who cauſe thee wander far abroad,</l>
                     <l>May from their wand'ring be reclaim'd to God.</l>
                     <l>Thoſe who from Earth purſue thee till thou die,</l>
                     <l>Endeavour to draw them to Heaven with thee.</l>
                     <l>Our bleſſed Lord, when hanging on the tree,</l>
                     <l>Prayed for thoſe who did him crucifie:</l>
                     <l>He to his Father for their pardon pray'd,</l>
                     <l>And did ſay for them all that could be ſaid.</l>
                     <l>How far was <hi>Stephen</hi> from leaving of his death</l>
                     <l>On thoſe who ſton'd him, witneſs his laſt breath:</l>
                     <l>He kneel'd, and cri'd, this ſin, Lord, do not lay</l>
                     <l>To their charge: Thus in love he ſlept away.</l>
                     <l>O lovely bleſſed ſleep! O ſure 'twill be</l>
                     <l>A heavenly thing in love to live and die.</l>
                     <l>Love is the way to Heaven, love is the flame</l>
                     <l>In which the ſoul ſurmounts the ſtarry frame.</l>
                     <l>This is the work and life of Saints above,</l>
                     <l>To love, and loved be; for God is love:</l>
                     <l>He's light and love, he freely doth impart</l>
                     <l>Light to the mind, and goodneſs to the heart.</l>
                     <l>With his reſplendent Glory fill thine eye,</l>
                     <l>And in his goodneſs place thou all thy Joy.</l>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:150340:37"/>
                     <l>Come ſee and taſte, Come, come, and taſte and ſee,</l>
                     <l>With goodneſs fill thy heart, with light thine eye.</l>
                     <l>The Father, Son and Spirit, Perſons three,</l>
                     <l>Who are in Eſſence one, do call on thee</l>
                     <l>To come from doleſome darkneſs unto light,</l>
                     <l>From ill to good, from ſorrow to delight;</l>
                     <l>From death to life, from guilt to righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</l>
                     <l>From the vile filth of ſin to holineſs;</l>
                     <l>From want to fullneſs; from weights which thee load,</l>
                     <l>To reſt and eaſe; from Satan unto God;</l>
                     <l>From Hell to Heaven, from luſts baſe drudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery,</l>
                     <l>To that high ſervice, God to glorifie.</l>
                     <l>Not that we can unto his Glory add;</l>
                     <l>For it is boundleſs. He hath ever had,</l>
                     <l>And hath, and ſhall have to Eternity</l>
                     <l>Perfection infinite, but that poor we,</l>
                     <l>With mind, heart, mouth, acknowledge and confeſs</l>
                     <l>His glory, as he doeth it expreſs</l>
                     <l>In all his Works, and in his holy Word,</l>
                     <l>And in the face of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord:</l>
                     <l>And that in eating, drinking, in each thing</l>
                     <l>We do, God's Glory we may ſtill deſign.</l>
                     <l>But ſurely it is wonderfully ſweet</l>
                     <l>To ſee Gods Glory and man's good unite.</l>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:150340:37"/>
                     <l>In theſe ſame acts by which they glorifie</l>
                     <l>The Lord, they do enjoy his company:</l>
                     <l>And theſe ſame acts which do unite the ſoul</l>
                     <l>Unto the Lord, his Glory do extol:</l>
                     <l>By acting Faith, and hoping in his Word,</l>
                     <l>They praiſe the Grace, Truth, Power of the Lord:</l>
                     <l>By acting Faith, they in their heart receive</l>
                     <l>The Lord to dwell in them, great peace they have:</l>
                     <l>Whoſe mind and heart upon the Lord is ſtaid,</l>
                     <l>Of evil tidings they are not afraid:</l>
                     <l>When they themſelves moſt quietly do hide</l>
                     <l>Under the ſhade of his wings, and abide</l>
                     <l>In the moſt ſecret place of the moſt high,</l>
                     <l>What harm of evil can to them come nigh?</l>
                     <l>Munition of Rocks doth them ſecure;</l>
                     <l>Their bread and water are to them made ſure:</l>
                     <l>God with broad Rivers them ſurrounds, that ſo</l>
                     <l>No Ship nor Galley can againſt them go.</l>
                     <l>Since in them God is Glory, and a wall</l>
                     <l>Of ſire about them, ſurely they have all,</l>
                     <l>Glory within their mind and heart to fill,</l>
                     <l>A fire without, to guard them from all ill.</l>
                     <l>How can they but be ſafe, who have ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</l>
                     <l>For VValls and Bulwarks, for their preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</l>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:150340:38"/>
                     <l>The more they truſt, the more they glorifie</l>
                     <l>God, and his wondrous loving kindneſs ſee,</l>
                     <l>Which he to them hath greatly magnified</l>
                     <l>Within a city that is fortified.</l>
                     <l>No outward force diſturbeth their ſolace,</l>
                     <l>When they thus guarded, ſee and taſte his grace.</l>
                     <l>Love doth at once the Lord himſelf embrace,</l>
                     <l>And glorifies his goodneſs, love and grace,</l>
                     <l>While we above all things the Lord do love,</l>
                     <l>We in our heart ſet him all things above,</l>
                     <l>While we deſire him, and do in him joy,</l>
                     <l>We move to him, and God himſelf enjoy:</l>
                     <l>Yea, every act whereby we glorifie</l>
                     <l>The Lord, in it we do the Lord draw nigh,</l>
                     <l>And God to us. Thus are his ſervants bleſt:</l>
                     <l>For all their ſervice is their intereſt.</l>
                     <l>Chriſt from himſelf ſervants ſent not away,</l>
                     <l>His word is come, follow me, with me ſtay:</l>
                     <l>If any ſerve me, let him follow me,</l>
                     <l>And where I am, there ſhall my ſervant be.</l>
                     <l>Since Chriſt is foremoſt, ſure the way is right:</l>
                     <l>Since he's the way, the Leader, and the Light,</l>
                     <l>The way is ſafe, take courage, talk no more</l>
                     <l>Of fear and danger, ſince God is before:</l>
                     <l>The way is pleaſant, it's a ſight moſt ſweet,</l>
                     <l>To ſee the ſteps of Jeſus lovely feet;</l>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:150340:38"/>
                     <l>And to walk in them, in them to walk on,</l>
                     <l>Since our fore-runner in theſe paths hath gone:</l>
                     <l>Tho he be gone before, yet he is near,</l>
                     <l>He's on the front, and alſo on the rear;</l>
                     <l>And ſtill on thy right hand thee to uphold:</l>
                     <l>Yea, in thy heart, to make thee humbly bold.</l>
                     <l>As he walks in them, this of them is crav'd,</l>
                     <l>That they walk in him, as they him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd.</l>
                     <l>It is his promiſe to be with them ſtill:</l>
                     <l>That they be ſtill with him, is his good will.</l>
                     <l>Thus all the ſervice he to them commends,</l>
                     <l>To Glory, Union, and Communion tends:</l>
                     <l>Their Maſter's Service is their intereſt,</l>
                     <l>In glorifying God they're truly bleſt:</l>
                     <l>This is thy chief end God to glorifie,</l>
                     <l>And to enjoy him to eternity.</l>
                     <l>Come to the Mediator Jeſus Chriſt,</l>
                     <l>In him alone the Lord with man's well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd.</l>
                     <l>Come unto God by him, though thou be'ſt loſt,</l>
                     <l>He will thee ſave unto the uttermoſt.</l>
                     <l>Come, take himſelf, and take his fulneſs all;</l>
                     <l>Deny thy ſelf, follow upon his call.</l>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:150340:39"/>
                     <l>Follow him fully, follow him with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light;</l>
                     <l>His yoke is eaſie, and his burden light:</l>
                     <l>His holy Ordinances are moſt ſweet,</l>
                     <l>His Rod is needful, and his Croſs is meet:</l>
                     <l>All ſervice he requires, is reaſonable,</l>
                     <l>All Rods and Croſſes needful, ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able:</l>
                     <l>It's only for a time, if need there be,</l>
                     <l>That trials come in great variety:</l>
                     <l>And though they ſadning be, yet they are bleſt,</l>
                     <l>And tend to Holineſs, Praiſe, Glory, Reſt.</l>
                     <l>Come, come, thy ſervice all, all thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs,</l>
                     <l>Is for God's Glory, and thy Happineſs.</l>
                     <l>Now ſince by God, the Father, and the Spirit,</l>
                     <l>Thou art from ſin and torments infinite,</l>
                     <l>Called to come, through Chriſt, the living way,</l>
                     <l>To Fellowſhip with God, which laſts for aye;</l>
                     <l>Behold, by whom, from what, through whom, to whom</l>
                     <l>Thou called art, all calls on thee to come:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Spirit and the Bride ſay, Come; let all who hear,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Say, Come; and let them come, who thirſty are:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:150340:39"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Here is Life's Fountain, whoſoever will,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of living water freely take thy fill.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That all who hear, may come, Lord, draw, that we</l>
                     <l>May come, and run, and follow after thee.</l>
                     <l>Come with thy Grace and Glory ſpeedily:</l>
                     <l>Lord Jeſus, come. <hi>Amen.</hi> So let it be.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150340:40"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150340:40"/>
                  <p>Twenty Five CONSIDERATIONS OF THE PAINS prepar'd for SIN After this Life.</p>
                  <p>WITH A SERMON <hi>Preached on</hi> Acts VII. 60.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>I heard a voice from Heaven, ſaying unto me, Write, From henceforth, Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, even ſo ſaith the Spirit; for they reſt from their labours, and their works follow them,</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Rev. 14.13.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Butler,</hi> in <hi>White-Lion-Court,</hi> in <hi>Barbican.</hi> 1688.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150340:41"/>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:150340:41"/>
                  <head>Twenty Five CONSIDERATIONS OF THE PAINS prepared for SIN After this Life.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. AMongſt all the means which God uſeth towards the Children of Men, to move them to this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, whereof I treat, the ſtrongeſt and moſt forcible (to the common ſort of men) is the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Puniſhments prepared by him for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious ſinners, and tranſgreſſors of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments. Wherefore he uſeth this Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration often, as may appear by all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who do nothing elſe almoſt but threaten
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150340:42"/>plagues and deſtruction to Offenders: And this means hath often times prevailed more than any others, that could be uſed, by reaſon of the Natural Love which we bear towards our ſelves; and conſequently the Natural Fears we have of our own danger. So we read, that nothing could move the <hi>Ninevites</hi> ſo much as the foretelling them of their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent deſtruction. And St. <hi>John the Baptist,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John <hi>the</hi> 5th. Matth. <hi>the</hi> 3d.</note> altho he came in a ſimple and contemptible way, yet preaching unto the people the terror of Vengeance to come, and that the Axe was now put to the Trees, to cut for the fire all thoſe which repented not; he moved the very <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Soldiers</hi> to fear, which otherwiſe are people of very hard metal; who came unto him upon his terrible Embaſſage, and asked, what they ſhould do to avoid theſe puniſhments?</p>
                  <p n="2">II. After then that we have conſidered of Death, and of God's ſevere Judgment, which enſueth after Death; and wherein every man hath to receive according to his works in this life, as the Scripture ſaith; it followeth, that we conſider alſo of the puniſhments which are appointed for them that ſhall be found faulty in that account. Hereby at leaſtwiſe no other conſideration will ſerve to induce
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150340:42"/>Chriſtians to this Reſolution of ſerving God: For as I have noted before, If every man have naturally a Love of himſelf, and deſire to conſerve his own eaſe, then ſhould he alſo have fear of peril, whereby he is to fall into extream calamity. This St. <hi>Bernard</hi> expreſſeth excellently, according to his cuſtom: <q rend="margQuotes">O man (ſaith he)! if thou haſt left all ſhame, which appertaineth to ſo noble a creature as thou art; if thou feeleſt no ſorrow, as car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal men do not, yet loſe not fear alſo, which is found in very beaſts. We uſe to load an Aſs, and weary him out with Labour, and he careth not, becauſe he is an Aſs: But if thou wouldeſt thruſt him into fire, or fling him into the ditch, he would avoid it as much as he could; for that he loveth life and feareth death. Fear thou then, and be not more inſenſible than a beaſt: Fear Death, fear Judgment, fear Hell. This Fear is called the beginning of Wiſdom; and not ſhame and ſorrow; for that the Spirit of fear is more mighty to reſiſt ſin, than the Spirit of ſhame or ſorrow. Wherefore it is ſaid; Remember the end, and thou ſhalt never ſin: That is, Remember the final pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments appointed for ſin after this life.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. Firſt therefore to ſpeak in General of the puniſhments reſerved for the Life to come:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:150340:43"/>If the Scriptures did not declare in particular their greatneſs unto us, That they are moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, dolorous, and intolerable: For firſt, as God is a God in all his Works; That is to ſay, great, wonderful, and terrible; ſo eſpecially he ſheweth the ſame in his puniſhments, being called for that cauſe in Scripture, a God of Juſtice, as alſo a God of Revenge. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing all his other Works are full of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and exceeding our capacities, we may likewiſe gather, that his hand in puniſhment muſt be wonderful: Alſo God himſelf teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us to reaſon in this manner, when he ſaith, <hi>And will ye not then fear me, and tremble before my face, which have put the ſand as a ſtop unto the ſea, and have given the water a command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment never to paſs, no, not when it is moſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and the floods moſt outragious:</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, If I am wonderful, and do paſs your imaginations in theſe works of the Sea, and others, which you ſee daily, you have cauſe to fear me, conſidering that my puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are like to be correſpondent to the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. Another conjecture of the great and ſevere Juſtice of God, may be the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his infinite and unſpeakable Mercy, the which, as it is the very Nature of God, and without end or meaſure, as his Godhead
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150340:43"/>is, ſo is alſo his Juſtice; and theſe two are the two arms, as it were, of God, embracing and kiſſing the one the other, as the Scripture ſaith: Therefore, as in a man of this world, if we had the meaſure of one arm, we might eaſily conjecture of the other: ſo ſeeing the wonderful examples daily of God's infinite mercy towards them that repent, we may imagine by the ſame his ſevere juſtice towards them whom he reſerveth to puniſhment in the next life, and whom for that cauſe he calleth in the Scriptures, Veſſels of his Fury, or Veſſels to ſhew his Fury upon.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. A Third Reaſon to perſwade us of the greatneſs of theſe puniſhments, may be the marvellous patience, and long-ſufferings of God in this life: As for example, in that he ſuffereth divers men, from one ſin to another, from one day to another, from one year to another, from one age to another, to ſpend (all I ſay) in diſhonour and deſpite of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; adding offence to offence, and refuſing all perſwaſions, allurements, good inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or other means of friendſhip that his mercy can deviſe, to offer for their amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And what man in the world could ſuffer this? Or what mortal heart can ſhew ſuch patience? But now if all this ſhould not be requited with ſeverity of puniſhment in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:150340:44"/>the world to come upon the obſtinate, it might ſeem againſt the Law of Juſtice and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and one arm of God might ſeem long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than the other. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this Reaſon in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> where he ſaith, <hi>Doſt thou not know, that the benignity of God is uſed to bring to repentance? And thou by thy hard and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent heart, doſt hoard up vengeance unto thy ſelf in the day of wrath, and appearance of God's just judgment, which ſhall restore to every man accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his works.</hi> He uſeth here the words of hoarding up of vengeance, to ſignifie, as a covetous man doth hoard up money to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney daily, to make his heap great, ſo the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repentant finner doth hoard up fin to fin; and God, on the contrary ſide, hoardeth up ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance to vengeance, until his meaſure be full, to reſtore in the meaſure againſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as the Prophet ſaith; and to pay us home, according to the multitude of our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations. This God meant, when he ſaid to <hi>Abraham,</hi> that the iniquity of the <hi>Amorites</hi> was not yet full up: Alſo in the Revelation unto St. <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt, when he uſeth this concluſion of that book: <hi>He that doth evil, let him do more evil; and he that liveth in filth, let him yet become more filthy: For behold, I come quickly, and my reward is with me, to render to every one according to his deeds.</hi> By
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:150340:44"/>which words God ſignifieth, that his bearing and tolerating with ſinners in this life, is an Argument of his greater ſeverity in the life to come; which the Prophet <hi>David</hi> alſo decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, when talking of a careleſs ſinner, he ſaith, <hi>The Lord ſhall ſcoff at him, foreſeeing that his day ſhall come.</hi> This day, no doubt, is to be underſtood the day of account, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment after this life: For ſo doth God more at large declare himſelf in theſe words:<note place="margin">Ezek. 7th.</note> 
                     <hi>And thou Son of man, this ſaith thy Lord God, The end is come; now (I ſay) the end is come upon thee: And I will ſhew in thee my fury, and will judge thee according to thy ways: I will lay against thee all thine abominations; and mine eye ſhall not ſpare thee, neither will I take any mercy upon thee; but I will put thy own ways upon thee, and thou ſhalt know that I am the Lord. Behold, afflictions cometh on; the end is come, the end, I ſay, is come; it hath watched against thee, and behold it is come: the day of ſlaughter is at hand: cruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is now come upon thee: Shortly will I pour out my wrath upon thee, and I will fill my fury in thee, and I will judge thee according to thy ways, and I will lay all thy wickedneſs upon thee: mine eye ſhall not pity thee, but I will lay thy way upon thee, and thine abominations in the midst of thee, and thou ſhalt know that I am the Lord that ſtriketh.</hi> Hitherto is the ſpeech of God himſelf.</p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:150340:45"/>
                  <p n="6">VI. Seeing then now we underſtand in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, that the puniſhments of God in the Life to come, are moſt certain to be great and ſevere to all ſuch as fall into them; for which cauſe the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>It is a fearful and horrible thing to fall into the hands of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God.</hi> Let us conſider ſomewhat in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, what manner of pains and puniſhments they ſhall be.</p>
                  <p n="7">VII. And firſt of all touching the place of puniſhment appointed for the Damned, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>Hell.</hi> The Scripture in divers Languages, uſeth divers Names, but all tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to expreſs the grievouſneſs of puniſhment there ſuffered, as in <hi>Latine</hi> it is called <hi>Infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> a place beneath, or under ground (as moſt of the Old Fathers do interpret): But whether it be under ground, or no, moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, that it is a place moſt oppoſite to Heaven, which is ſaid to be above. And this Name is uſed, to ſignifie the miſerable ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing, and hurling down of the damned, to be trodden under the feet, not only of God, but of good men alſo, for ever: For ſo ſaith the Scripture: <hi>Behold the day of the Lord cometh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mal. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>burning like a furnace, and proud and wicked men ſhall be as ſtraw to that furnace, and you that fear my name ſhall tread them down, and they
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:150340:45"/>ſhall be as burnt aſhes under the ſoles of your feet in that day.</hi> And this ſhall be one of the greateſt miſeries that can happen to the proud and ſtout Potentates of the World, to be thrown with ſuch contempt down, and to be trodden under feet of them whom they ſo much deſpiſed in this world.</p>
                  <p n="8">VIII. The <hi>Hebrew</hi> word which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture uſeth for Hell is <hi>(Seol),</hi> which ſignifieth a great Ditch or Dungeon: In which ſenſe it is called in the <hi>Apocalyps, The lake of the wrath of God:</hi> And again, <hi>A poole burning with fire and brimſtone.</hi> In <hi>Greek</hi> the Scripture uſeth Three words for the ſame place: the firſt is <hi>(Clades),</hi> uſed in the Goſpel, which (as <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> noteth) ſignifieth a place where no light is; the ſecond is <hi>(Zophoz),</hi> in St. <hi>Peter,</hi> which ſignifieth darkneſs it ſelf: in which ſenſe it is alſo called of <hi>Job,</hi> a dark land overwhelmed with deadly obſcurity: Alſo in the Goſpel, <hi>utter darkneſs.</hi> The third <hi>Greek</hi> word is <hi>(Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taros),</hi> uſed alſo by St. <hi>Peter:</hi> which word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing derived of the Verb, <hi>Taraſſo,</hi> which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to terrifie, trouble and vex, importeth an horrible confuſion of Tormentors in that place, even as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith of it, <hi>There dwelleth no order, but everlaſting horror.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:150340:46"/>
                  <p n="9">IX. The <hi>Chaldee</hi> word, which is alſo uſed in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and tranſlated to the <hi>Greek,</hi> is <hi>(Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henna),</hi> firſt of all uſed by Chriſt for the place of them which are damned, as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth upon the Tenth Chapter of St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Goſpel. And this word being compounded of <hi>Gee</hi> and <hi>Hinnom,</hi> ſignifieth a Valley nigh to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> called, the Valley. <hi>Hinnom;</hi> in which the old idolatrous <hi>Jews</hi> were wont to bury alive their own children, in the honour of the Devil, and to ſound with Trumpets, Timbrels, and other loud Inſtruments, whilſt they were doing thereof, that their childrens Voices might not be heard; which place was afterwards uſed for the receit of all filthineſs, as Dung, dead Carrions, and the like: And it is moſt probable, that our Saviour uſed this word, above all other, for Hell, thereby to ſignifie the miſerable burning of Souls in that place, the pitiful clamours and cries of the tormented, the confuſed and barbarous noiſe of the tormentors, together with the moſt loathſome filthineſs of the place, which is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe deſcribed in the Scripture, by the Names of Addars, Snakes, Cockatrices, Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, and other venemous creatures, as ſhall be afterwards declared.</p>
                  <p n="10">X. Having declared the Names of this place and thereby alſo in ſome part, the Nature; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:150340:46"/>remaineth now, that we confider, what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of pains men ſuffer there. For conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof, we muſt note, That as Heaven and Hell are contrary, aſſigned to contrary perſons, for contrary cauſes; ſo have they in all reſpects, contrary properties, conditions, and effects, in ſuch ſort, as whatſoever is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Felicity of the one, may ſerve to infer the contrary of the other, as when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>No eye hath ſeen, nor ear heard, nor heart conceived the Joys that God hath prepared for them that ſhall be ſaved,</hi> we may infer, that the pains of the damned muſt be as great again, when the Scripture ſaith, the felicity of them in Heaven, is a perfect felicity, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>omne bonum,</hi> all goodneſs; ſo that no one kind of pleaſure can be imagined, which they have not.</p>
                  <p>We muſt think on the contrary part, that the miſery of the damned muſt be alſo a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect miſery, containing all afflictions that may be, without wanting any: So that as the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the good is infinite and univerſal, ſo alſo the calamity of the wicked is infinite and univerſal. Now in this life all the miſeries and pains which fall upon men, are but parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and not univerſal: As for Example, We ſee one man pained in his Eyes, another in his Back, which particular pains, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſometimes are ſo extream, as life is
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:150340:47"/>not able to reſiſt them, and a man would ſuffer them long for the gaining of many Worlds together: But ſuppoſe a man were now tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in all the parts of his body at once, as in his Head, his Eyes, his Tongue, his Teeth, his Throat, his Stomach, his Belly, his Back, his Heart, his Sides, his Thighs, and in all the Joints of his Body: Beſides, ſuppoſe (I ſay) he were moſt cruelly tormented with extream pains in all theſe parts together, without eaſe or intermiſſion, what thing could be more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable than this? What ſight more lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? If thou ſhouldeſt ſee a Dog lie ſo in the ſtreet, ſo afflicted, I know thou couldeſt not but take compaſſion upon him. Well then, conſider what difference there is between abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theſe pains for a Week, or for all Eternity; in ſuffering them upon a ſoft Bed, or upon a burning Gridiron, and boiling Furnace; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong a man's Friends, comforting him, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Furies of Hell whipping him. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this (I ſay), gentle Reader, and if thou wouldeſt take a great deal of labour, rather than abide the one in this life, be content to ſuſtain a little pain, rather than to incur the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the life to come.</p>
                  <p n="11">XI. But to conſider theſe things yet further, not only all theſe parts of the body, which have been inſtruments to ſin, ſhall be torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:150340:47"/>together, but alſo every-ſenſe, both exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and internal, for the ſame cauſe, ſhall be afflicted with his particular torment, contrary to the Object, wherein it took moſt pleaſure and delight in this World: As for Example; The Eyes were afflicted with the ugly and fearful fight of Devils, the delicate Ears with the horrible noiſe of the damned Spirits, the nice ſmell with poiſoned ſtench of brimſtone, the dainty taſte with moſt ravenous hunger and thirſt; and all the ſenſible parts of the body with burning fire. Again, the Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be tormented with the apprehenſion of pains preſent and to come, the Memory with the remembrance of pleaſures paſt, the Underſtanding with conſideration of the feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city loſt, and the miſery now to come on. O poor Chriſtian! what wilt thou do amidſt the multitude of ſo grievous calamities.</p>
                  <p n="12">XII. It is a wonderful matter, and able, as one Father ſaith, to make a reaſonable man go out of his wits, to conſider what God hath revealed unto us in the Scriptures, of the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful circumſtances of this puniſhment; and yet to ſee how little wretchleſs men of this world do fear it. For firſt, touching the univerſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, verity and greatneſs of the pain, not only the Reaſons before alledged, but alſo divers Conſiderations in the Scriptures do declare:
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:150340:48"/>As where it is ſaid of the damned, <hi>They ſhall be tormented day and night.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.14.</note> And again,<note place="margin">Rev. <hi>20.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Give her torment,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Babylon</hi> in Hell, by which is ſignified, that the pains in Hell are not exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for chaſtiſement, but for torment of the parties: And torments commonly, we ſee in this world to be as great and extream as the Wit of a man can reach to deviſe. Imagine then,<note place="margin">Luke <hi>16.</hi>
                     </note> when God ſhall lay his head to deviſe torments, as he hath done in Hell, what manner of torments will they be.</p>
                  <p n="13">XIII. If creating an Element here for our comfort, I mean the fire, he could create the ſame ſo terrible, as it is in ſuch ſort, as a man would not hold his only hand in it, to gain a Kingdom; what a fire think you hath he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for Hell, which is not created for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, but for torment of the parties? Our fire hath many differences from that, and therefore is truly ſaid of the holy Fathers, to be but a painted and feigned fire, in reſpect of that: for our fire was made to comfort us, as I have ſaid, and that to torment: Our fire hath need to be fed continually with wood, or elſe it goeth out; that burneth continually, without feeding: Ours giveth light, that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth none: Ours is out of his natural place, and therefore ſhifteth to aſcend, and to get
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:150340:48"/>from us, as we ſee; but this is in the natural place where it was created; and therefore it abideth there perpetually: Ours conſumeth the matter laid in it, and ſo quickly diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the pain; that tormenteth, but conſumeth not, to the end, the pain may be everlaſting: Our fire is extinguiſhed with water, and aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted greatly by the coolneſs of the Air about it: that hath no ſuch abatement or qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Finally, what a ſtrange and incredible kind of fire that is, as appeareth by theſe words of our Saviour ſo often repeated? <hi>There ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> Weeping is to be referred to the effect of extream burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the fire; for that the torment of ſcald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and burning enforceth Tears ſooner than any other torment, as appeareth in them which upon a ſudden do put an hot thing into their mouth, or ſcald any other part of their body; and gnaſhing of their teeth, or chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, at leaſt, as every man knoweth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth of great and extream cold. Imagine then what fire this is, which hath ſuch extream effects both of heat and cold. O mighty Lord, what a ſtrange God art thou! how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful and terrible in all thy works and inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions! how bountiful art thou to thoſe that love and fear thee! how ſevere to them that contemn thy Commandments! Haſt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed a way how they that lie burning in the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:150340:49"/>lake of fire and brimſtone, ſhall be tormented with extream cold? What underſtanding of man can conceive how this may be? But thy Judgments, O Lord, are a depth without bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom; and therefore I leave this to thine own providence, praiſing thee eternally for the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="14">XIV. Beſides theſe general pains, common to all that be in that place, the Scripture ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth alſo, that there ſhall be particular tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, peculiar both in quality and quantity to the ſins and offences of each offender: for to that end ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 17. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28. to God: <hi>Thou wilt judge in meaſure againſt meaſure.</hi> And God ſaith of himſelf, <hi>I will exerciſe judgment in weight and juſtice in meaſure.</hi> And this is the meaning of all thoſe threats of God to ſinners, where he ſaith, he will pay them home according to their particular works, and according to the inventions of their own hearts. In this ſence it is ſaid in <hi>Revel.</hi> 18. of <hi>Babylon</hi> now thrown down into the Lake; <hi>Look how much ſhe hath glorified her ſelf, and hath lived in delights, ſo much torment and affliction give her.</hi> Whereof the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have gathered the variety of torments that ſhall be in that place, ſaith old <hi>Ephraim:</hi> As if the Adulterer ſhould have one kind of torment, the Murderer another, the Thief
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:150340:49"/>another, the Drunkard another, the Lyar an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: As if the proud man ſhould be trodden under feet, to recompence his pride, the Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton ſuffer ineſtimable hunger, the Drunkard extream thirſt, the delicious mouth filled up with gall, and the delicate body feared with hot burning Irons.</p>
                  <p n="15">XV. The Holy Ghoſt ſignifieth ſuch a thing, when he ſaith in the Scriptures of the wicked worldling, His bread in his belly ſhall be turned into Gall of Serpents;<note place="margin">Job <hi>20.</hi>
                     </note> he ſhall be conſtrained to ſpue out again the riches which he hath devoured: nay, God ſhall pull them out of his belly again: He ſhall be conſtrained to ſuck the Gall of Cockatrices, and the Tongue of an Adder ſhall kill him; he ſhall pay ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for all that ever he hath done, and yet ſhall not be conſumed; but ſhall ſuffer according to the multitude of all his devices: utter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs lieth in wait for him, and fire which needeth no kindling ſhall eat him up. This is the wicked man's portion from God. By which words, and ſuch like, is plainly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that worldlings ſhall receive, as it were, particular and proper torments, for their glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, for their delicate fare, for their extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the like; which torments ſhall be greater than any worldly Tongue can expreſs,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150340:50"/>as may appear by the vehement and horrible words which the Holy Ghoſt here uſeth, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="16">XVI. Beſides this, the Scripture ſheweth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, not only the univerſality, particularity, and ſeverity of theſe pains, but alſo the ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof, without aid or help, eaſe or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, when he ſaith, we ſhall be caſt in bound hand and feet: For it is ſome kind of comfort in this world, to be able to reſiſt or ſtrive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our afflictions: but here we muſt lie ſtill, and ſuffer all. Again, when he ſaith, <hi>Clauſa eſt Janua,</hi> the Gate is ſhut: that is, the Gate of all Mercy, all Pardon, of all Eaſe, of all Intermiſſion, of all Comfort, is ſhut up from Heaven, from Earth, from the Creator, and from Creatures, inſomuch as no conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ever to be hoped for any more, as in all the miſeries of this life there is always ſome. This ſtraitneſs is moſt lively expreſſed in that dreadful Parable of the Rich Glutton in Hell, who was driven to that neceſſity, as he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that <hi>Lazarus</hi> might dip the top of his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in water, to cool his Tongue, in the midſt of that fire wherein he ſaith he was; and yet could he not obtain it. A ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing it ſeemeth it would have been unto him, if he had obtained, the ſame: but, to ſhew the ſtraitneſs of the place, it was denied
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:150340:50"/>him. O you that live in the ſinful wealth of the world, conſider but this one Example of God's ſeverity, and be afraid. This man was in great Royalty a little before, and nothing regarded the extream miſery that <hi>Lazarus</hi> was in: But would he give a thouſand worlds, if he had them, for one drop of water to cool his Tongue. What demand could be leſs than this? He durſt not ask to be delivered thence, or to have his torments diminiſhed, or to ask a great Veſſel of water to refreſh his whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy therein, but only ſo much as would ſtick on the top of a man's finger, to cool his Tongue. To what need was this man dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that was ſo rich before! What a great imagination had he of the force of one drop of water! To what a pitiful change was his Tongue now come unto, that was wont to be ſo diligently applied with all kinds of pleaſant Liquors! O that one man could take example by another. Either this is true, or elſe the Son of God is a Liar. And then, what men are we, that ſeeing our ſelves in danger of this miſery, do not ſeek with more diligence to avoid the ſame?</p>
                  <p n="17">XVII. In reſpect of theſe extremities, and ſtrait dealings of God, in denying all comfort and conſolation at this day, the Scripture ſaith, that men ſhall fall into rage, fury, and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:150340:51"/>utter impatience, blaſpheming God, and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the day of their Nativity; with eating their own Tongues for grief, and deſiring the Rocks and Mountains to come and fall on them, to end them of their pains.</p>
                  <p n="18">XVIII. Now if we add to this the eternity and everlaſting continuance of theſe torments, we ſhall ſee that it increaſeth the matter great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for in this world there is no torment ſo great, but that time either taketh away, or diminiſheth the ſame: for either the tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, or the tormented dieth, or ſome occaſion or other happeneth to alter or mitigate the matter; but here is no ſuch hope or comfort: but, ſaith the Scriptures, they ſhall be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented for ever in a pool burning with fire and brimſtone: As long as God is God, ſo long ſhall they burn; there ſhall neither the tormentor or the tormented die, but both live eternally, for the eternal miſery of the parties to be puniſhed.</p>
                  <p n="19">XIX. <q rend="margQuotes">Oh! ſaith one of the Fathers, in a godly Meditation, if a ſinner damned in Hell, did know that he had to ſuffer thoſe torments there no more thouſands of years than there be Sands in the Sea, and Graſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piles on the ground, or no more thouſands of millions of Ages, than there be Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:150340:51"/>in Heaven and Earth, he would great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejoice thereof; for then he would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort himſelf, at the leaſt, with this Cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that once the matter would have an end: But now, ſaith this good man, this word never breaketh his heart when he thinketh on it: And after an hundred thouſand milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Worlds there ſuffered, he hath as far to his end as he had at the firſt day of his entrance to theſe torments.</q> Conſider (good Chriſtians) what a length an hour would ſeem to thee, if thou had'ſt but to hold thy hand in fire and brimſtone only during the ſpace there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. We ſee if a man be grievouſly ſick, tho he be laid on a very ſoft bed, yet one Night ſeemeth a long time unto him; he turneth and toſſeth himſelf from ſide to ſide, telling the Clock, and counting the hours as they paſs, which ſeemeth to him a whole day: And if a man ſhould ſay unto him, that he were to abide that pain but ſeven years together, he would go well nigh to deſpair for grief. Now if one Night ſeem ſo long and tedious to him that lieth on a good ſoft bed, and afflicted on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a little Ague, what will the lying in fire and brimſtone do, when he ſhall know e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently, that he ſhall never have end thereof. O (dear Brother)! the ſatiety of continuance is loathſome, even in things that are not evil of themſelves; if thou ſhouldeſt always be
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:150340:52"/>bound to eat one meat, it would be diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to thee in the end; if thou ſhould'ſt be bound to ſit ſtill all thy life in one place, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out moving, it would be grievous unto thee, albeit no man did torment thee in that place: What then will it be to lie eternally; that is, world without end, in moſt exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Is it any way tolerable? What Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then, what Wit, what Diſcretion is there left in man, which makes no more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this matter than they do.</p>
                  <p n="20">XX. I might here add another circumſtance which the Scripture addeth, to wit, that all theſe torments ſhall be in darkneſs, a thing dreadful of it ſelf to man's Nature: For there is not the ſtouteſt man in the world, if he be found himſelf alone, and naked, in extream darkneſs, and ſhould hear a noiſe of Spirits coming towards him, but he would fear, albeit he felt never a laſh from them on his body. I might alſo add another circumſtance that the Prophet addeth, which is, that God and good men ſhall laugh at them that day, which will be no ſmall affliction: For as to be moaned by a man's friends in time of adverſity, is ſome comfort, ſo to be laughed at, eſpecially by him who only may help him, is a great and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable increaſe of his mifery.</p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:150340:52"/>
                  <p n="21">XXI. And now all this that I have ſpoken of hitherto, is but one part of a damned man's puniſhment only, called by Divines, <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Senſus,</hi> the pain of ſence or feeling; that is, the pain or puniſhment ſenſibly inflicted on the ſoul and body. But yet beſides this, there is another part of puniſhment, called <hi>Poena damni,</hi> the pain of loſs or damage, which, by all Learned mens Opinions, is either greater, or no leſs than the former. And this is the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite loſs which a damned man hath, in being excluded for ever and ever from the ſight of his Creator, and his Glory, which ſight only being ſufficient to make happy and bleſſed all them that are admitted unto it, muſt needs be an infinite miſery to the damned man, to lack that eternally: And therefore this is put as one of the chiefeſt and firſt plagues to be laid upon him:<note place="margin">Iſa. <hi>26.</hi>
                     </note> Let the wicked man be taken away to Hell, to the end he may not ſee the Glory of God. And this loſs containeth all other loſſes and damages in it, as the loſs of Eternal Bliſs and Joy (as I have ſaid), of Eternal Glory, of Eternal Society with the Angels, and the like; which loſſes, when a damned man conſidereth (as he cannot but conſider them ſtill), he taketh more grief thereof (as Divines do hold) than by all the ſenſible torments that he abides beſide.</p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:150340:53"/>
                  <p n="22">XXII. Whereunto belongs the Worm of Conſcience, in Scripture ſo called: For as a Worm lieth eating and gnawing wood, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhe lieth, ſo ſhall the remorſe of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience lie within us, griping and tormenting us for ever. And this worm of remorſe ſhall principally conſiſt in bringing to our minds all the means and cauſes of our preſent extream calamities, as our negligences, whereby we loſt the felicity which other men have gotten. And at every one of theſe Conſiderations this worm ſhall give us a deadly bite, even unto the heart; as when it ſhall lay before us all the occaſions that we had ſuffer'd to avoid this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery wherein we are now fallen, and to have gotten the glory which we have loſt. How eaſie it had been to have done it! how nigh were we oftentimes to reſolve our ſelves to do it, and yet how ungraciouſly we left off that Cogitation again! How many times we were foretold of this danger, and yet how little care and fear we took in the ſame? How vain the worldly trifles were wherein we ſpent our time, and for which we loſt Heaven, and fell into this intolerable miſery? How are they exalted whom we thought Fools in this world, and how are we now proved Fools, and laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at, which thought our ſelves wiſe. Theſe things (I ſay), and a thouſand more, being laid before us by our own Conſcience, ſhall
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:150340:53"/>yield us infinite grief, for that it is now too late to amend them. This grief is called the Worm or remorſe of our Conſcience, which worm ſhall enforce men more to weep and howl, than any torment elſe, conſidering how negligently, fooliſhly, and vainly, they are come into thoſe inſupportable torments, and that now there is no more time to redrefs their Errors. Theſe are the Cogitations of the damned in Hell.</p>
                  <p n="23">XXIII. Now only is the time of weeping, for theſe men, and their lamenting but all in vain. Now ſhall they begin to fret and fume, and marvel at themſelves, ſaying, Where were our Wits, where was our Underſtanding, where was our Judgment, when we followed vanities, and contemned theſe things? This is the talk of ſinners in Hell. Saith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>What hath our pride, or what hath the glory of Riches profited us? they are all now vaniſhed, now like a ſhadow: We have wearied our ſelves in the way of iniquity and perdition, but the way of the Lord we have not known.</hi> This, I ſay, muſt be that Everlaſting Song of the damned worm eaten Conſcience in Hell. Mark, good Reader, Eternal Repentance without profit, whereby we ſhall be brought to ſuch deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the Scripture noteth; as he ſhall turn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fury againſt himſelf, tear his own fleſh,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:150340:54"/>rent his own ſoul, if it were poſſible, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite the Fiends of Hell to torment him, ſeeing he hath ſo beaſtly behaved himſelf in this world, as not to provide in time for this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal matter. O! if he could have another life to live in this world again, how would he paſs it over! with what diligence, with what ſeverity! But it is not lawful: We only which are yet alive have that ſingular benefit, if we know it, or would reſolve our ſelves to make the moſt of it: one of theſe days we ſhall be paſt it alſo, and ſhall not recover it again; no, not one hour, if we would give a thouſand worlds for the ſame, as indeed the damned would do, if they might. Let us now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo uſe the benefit of our preſent time, as when we are paſt hence, we have not need to wiſh our ſelves here again.</p>
                  <p n="24">XXIV. Now is the time we may avoid all; now is the time we may put our ſelves out of danger of theſe matters (I ſay), now, if we reſolve our ſelves out of hand; for we know not what ſhall become of us to morrow: It may be to morrow our hearts will be as hard and careleſs of theſe things as they have been heretofore, and as <hi>Parcab</hi>'s heart after <hi>Moſes</hi>'s departure from him. O that he had reſolved himſelf throughly whilſt <hi>Moſes</hi> was with him, how happy had he been! If the Rich Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:150340:54"/>had taken the time while he was in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, how bleſſed a man had he been! He was foretold of his miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,<note place="margin">Luke <hi>16.</hi>
                     </note> as we are now by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, as Chriſt ſignifieth; but he would not hear. Afterwards he was in ſuch admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his own Folly, that he would have had <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſent from <hi>Abraham</hi>'s boſome unto his brethren, to warn them of his ſucceſs: But <hi>Abraham</hi> told him it was bootleſs; for they would not have believed <hi>Lazarus,</hi> but rather have perſecuted him as a Liar, and defamer of their honourable Brother's death, if he ſhould have come and told them of his torments: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſo would the wicked of this world do now, if one ſhould come and tell them, that their Parents and Friends were damned in Hell, for ſuch and ſuch things, and do beſeech them to look better to their Lives, to the end, that their coming, they do not increaſe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers pains, for being ſome cauſe of their dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. (for this is only the cauſe of care which the damned have towards the living, and not for any love they now bear them) If (I ſay) ſuch a meſſage ſhould come from Hell to the flouriſhing ſinners in this World, would not they laugh at it? Would not they perſecute eagerly the parties that ſhould bring ſuch news? What then can God deviſe to do for the ſaving of theſe men? What way, what means may
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:150340:55"/>he take, when neither Warning nor Example of others, nor Threats, nor Exhortations will do any good? We know, or may know, that leading the life that we do, we cannot be ſaved; We know, or ought to know, that many before us have been damned for leſs matters; We know, and cannot chuſe but know, that we muſt ſhortly die, and receive our ſelves as they have received, living as they did, or worſe. We ſee, by this laid down before us, that the pains are intolerable, and yet Eternal which do expect us: for the ſame, we confeſs them moſt miſerable, that for any pleaſure or commodity of this world, are now fallen into thoſe pains. What then ſhould let us then to reſolve to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch our ſelves quickly of all impediments; to break violently from all bonds and chains of this wicked world, that do let us from this true and zealous work and ſervice of God? Why ſhould we ſleep one Night in ſin, ſeeing that might be our laſt Night, and ſo the everlaſting cutting off all hope for the life to come.</p>
                  <p n="25">XXV. Reſolve thy ſelf therefore, my dear Brother, if thou be wiſe, and clear thy ſell from this imminent danger, while God is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to receive thee, and moveth thee there un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by theſe means, as he did the rich man by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, while he was yet in his proſperity. Let his Example be often before
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:150340:55"/>thine eyes, and conſider it throughly, and it ſhall do thee good. God is a wonderful God, and to ſhew his patience and infinite goodneſs, he wooeth us in this life, ſeeketh unto us, and layeth himſelf (as it were) at our feet, to move us unto our own good, to win us, to draw us, and ſave us from perdition. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life he altereth his courſe of dealing, he turneth over the leaf, and changeth his ſtile, of a Lamb he becometh a Lion to the wicked, and of a Saviour a juſt and ſevere puniſher. What can be ſaid or done more to move us, that is forewarned, and ſeeth his own danger before his face, and yet is not ſtirred, and made more wary, or fearful thereby, but notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, will come, or ſlide into the ſame, may well be pitied, but ſurely by no means can be helped, making himſelf incapable of remedies that may be uſed.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150340:56"/>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:150340:56"/>
                  <head>A SERMON.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Acts VII. 60.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>And when he had ſaid this he fell aſleep.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THeſe words contain in them the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py cloſure and upſhot of <hi>Stephen</hi>'s life, wherein we have Three Particulars:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>The Perſon that fell aſleep.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>The Speech he made when he fell aſleep.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>What he did when he had finiſhed his Speech.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:150340:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>First,</hi> We have the Perſon that fell aſleep, and that was <hi>Stephen.</hi> He was a man full of Faith, and full of the Holy Ghoſt, as you may ſee, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.5. He was the firſt Martyr that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſuffered for the Cauſe of Chriſt. Hence I might gather this Doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That the beſt of men are ſubject to ſudden and violent Deaths.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Stephen,</hi> that was full of the Holy Ghoſt, was ſtoned to death, and <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> that was full of the Holy Ghoſt from the very Womb, was beheaded; <hi>Peter</hi> was crucified, and ſo was <hi>Andrew; Iſaiah</hi> was ſawed aſunder, <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> was ſtoned, and <hi>Zacharias</hi> was ſlain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Temple and the Altar. But I ſhall paſs this.</p>
                  <p>The Second part of the Text is the Speech that <hi>Stephen</hi> made when he fell aſleep; <hi>Hcc di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte obdormivit:</hi> That is, when he had finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Prayer, he fell aſleep. Hence obſerve this, That it is an excellent way to cloſe up our Life with prayer. To die praying is a moſt Chriſtian way of dying; the ſtoned <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> calling upon God. After this manner Chriſt died: he prayed, <hi>Father, into thy hands I commend my Spirit, and having thus ſaid, he gave up the Ghoſt.</hi> This he did, that it might
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:150340:57"/>be a pattern to all Chriſtians. Prayer is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary duty at all times, but eſpecially when we are a dying: And that for theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe when we are to die, we have moſt need of God's help: for then the Devil is moſt buſie, and we moſt weak.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe when we are to die, we are to beg the greateſt boon of God that is, That he would receive us into his Heavenly Kingdom. Now Prayer is the chief means to obtain this mercy: for it is <hi>Porta Caeli, Clavis Paradici,</hi> the Gate of Heaven, a Key to let us into Paradice. Therefore we have great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to die praying.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Becauſe when a Saint of God is dying, he is then to take his laſt farewel of Prayer. In Heaven there is no praying, but all thankſgiving: There is no need in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, therefore no praying in Heaven now, a Saint of God being to take his leave of prayer, when he is to die, therefore it is fit to die pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>I beſeech you remember this pattern in the Text, St. <hi>Stephen</hi> died calling upon God. Let us die praying, as that Emperor ſaid, <hi>Oportes Imperatorem ſtantem mori.</hi> So may I ſay, <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet Chriſtianum mori precantem;</hi> It behoves a Chriſtian to die praying.</p>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:150340:58"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> But what was the Subſtance of <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi>'s prayer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> He prayed for himſelf, <hi>Lord Jeſus, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive my Spirit, ver.</hi> 59. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He prayed for his perſecutors; <hi>Lord, lay not this ſin to their charge,</hi> ver. 60.</p>
                  <p>I will not enter upon this part of the Text, for it would ſwallow up all my time: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall wave it, and come to the Third part, which is that, that by God's aſſiſtance I purpoſe to ſpeak unto, to wit, what <hi>Stephen</hi> did when he had finiſhed his Prayer: <hi>When he had ſaid this, he fell aſleep;</hi> that is, he died. Behold here the Magnanimity, the Piety, and the Chriſtian Courage of <hi>Stephen:</hi> The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were ſtoning of him, and gnaſhing their Teeth upon him: and the good man dies with as much quietneſs of mind as if he had died on his bed: He fell aſleep while they were ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him; while he died he prayed, and while he prayed he died.</p>
                  <p>But what made <hi>Stephen</hi> die thus quietly? Read the <hi>55th Verſe,</hi> and you ſhall ſee the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it: <hi>Being full of the Holy Ghoſt, he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up ſtedfaſtly into Heaven, and ſaw the glory of God and Jeſus ſtanding at the right hand of God.</hi> This made him die with ſuch a ſweet, quiet, and calm Temper; he ſaw Jeſus Chriſt ſtanding at the Right Hand of God, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to receive his Soul, and that made him to
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:150340:58"/>die with ſuch an extraordinary quietneſs of mind.</p>
                  <p>Death in Scripture, eſpecially the death of God's Children, is often compared to a ſleep: It is ſaid of <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.10. that <hi>he ſlept with his Fathers.</hi> And it is ſaid, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.3. <hi>I would not have you ignorant concerning them that are aſleep;</hi> that is, concerning them that are dead. And 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 11.50. <hi>For this cauſe many are weakly and ſick among you, and many ſleep;</hi> that is, many die. This Expreſſion is a Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorical Expreſſion, and will afford us many rare and pretious Inſtructions: And therefore, the Grace of God aſſiſting me, I deſire to ſpend the reſt of the time in opening this Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor.</p>
                  <p>The Doctrine is this, <hi>viz. That when a child of God dies, though his death be never ſo unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and violent, yet it is nothing but a falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep.</hi> Or, <hi>A Child of God, though ſtoned to death, though burnt to aſhes, though it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo violent, or unnatural, is nothing but a fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſleep:</hi> When he had ſaid this, he fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Somnus eſt mortis Imago;</hi> Sleep is the Image of Death. There are many notable reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances betwixt ſleep and death, ſome of which I ſhall ſpeak of at this time.</p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:150340:59"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Sleep is common to all men: no man can live without ſleep: A man may live long without meat, but no man can live long with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſleep. So it is true with death; Death is common too: <hi>It is appointed for all men once to dis:</hi> and therefore <hi>David</hi> ſaith, he was to go the way of all fleſh. <hi>Statutum eſt omnibus ſemel mori: omnibus eſt calcanda ſemel Lethivia:</hi> All men muſt ſleep the ſleep of Death, or elſe be changed, which is a metaphorical death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> As ſleep ariſeth from the Vapours that aſcend from the Stomach to the Head, and tie the Senſes, and hinder their Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſo Death came into the World by <hi>Adam</hi>'s eating the Forbidden Fruit, and by the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonful Vapour of ſin, that brought death up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and all his Poſterity: <hi>By one man, ſin entred into the world, and death by ſin, and ſo death paſſed upon all men, for that all have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> Rom. 5.12. Had <hi>Adam</hi> never ſinned, <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould never have died: But, <hi>in illo die,</hi> ſaid God; <hi>But in that day thou eateſt the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruit, thou ſhalt die the death.</hi> Sin brings <hi>omni modam mortem,</hi> all kinds of death; it brings death temporal, death ſpiritual, and death eternal. Now becauſe all men are poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with the poiſon of ſin, therefore all men muſt ſleep of the ſleep of death: It is ſin that hath poiſoned all mankind.</p>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:150340:59"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As a man when he goeth to ſleep, puts off his Cloaths, and goeth naked into bed; ſo it is with us when we come to die: We came naked into the World, and naked we muſt return; As we brought nothing with us into the World, ſo we muſt carry nothing with us out of the World: And therefore Death in Scripture is called nothing elſe but an uncloathing of our ſelves, as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. Death to a Child of God, is nothing but the putting off of his Cloaths: The Body of man is <hi>Animae &amp; veſtimentum;</hi> it is the Soul's cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: and Death is nothing elſe but the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloathing of the Soul: It is juſt like a man go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to bed, and putting of his cloaths. St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> calls it, the putting off of our earthly Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 1.14. Our Bodies are the Souls Tabernacles, and death is the putting off of this Tabernacle.</p>
                  <p>Beloved, when we come to die, we ſhall be ſtript naked of Three things:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> We ſhall be ſtript naked of all our Worldly Honour, Riches and Greatneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> We ſhall be ſtript naked of our Bodies.</p>
                  <p>And, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Which is above all, we ſhall be ſtript naked of our ſins, and that is the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of a child of God; he ſhall put off not only his mortal body, but the body of ſin.</p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:150340:60"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> In the Fourth place, obſerve, As no man knoweth the time when he falls aſleep, a man falls aſleep before he is aware; ſo no man can tell the certain time when he muſt die. There is nothing ſo certain as that we muſt die, nothing ſo uncertain as the time when we ſhall die: Death comes ſuddenly, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as ſleep comes on a man before he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Obſerve, as Children and Infants, becauſe they do not know the benefit of ſleep, are very loth to go to bed; yea, many times the Mother is fain to whip the Child to bed: even ſo it is with moſt of God's People, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not ſtudy the benefit of death: That death puts an end to all our miſeries and ſins, and opens a door to let us into everlaſting happineſs, and that we ſhall never ſee God or Chriſt until we die. I ſay, becauſe God's People do not ſtudy the benefit of death, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are like to little children, loth to die,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Job</hi> 18.14.</note> loth to go to bed; and therefore Death is called, the <hi>King of Terrors.</hi> Death is terrible to many of God's Children, becauſe they are but Infants in Grace, and becauſe they do not know the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Obſerve, as when a man is faſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, he is free from cares and troubles. Let it thunder, as it thundered not long ſince, as
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:150340:60"/>you know, yet a man that is faſt aſleep, he hears it not. Let the Houſe be on fire while the man is aſleep, he ſees it not, neither is he troubled at it: So it is with the death of God's Children; When God's Children ſleep the ſleep of death, they are free from the thunders of this World, and from all cares and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles: they go to their Graves as to their Beds, and reſt in quietneſs, and are not ſenſible of any troubles that are in this World; <hi>for Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham knows us not, Iſa.</hi> 63.16. ſo 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.20. <hi>Thou ſhalt be gathered into thy grave in peace, and thy eyes ſhall not ſee all the evil that I will bring upon this place.</hi> When a Child of God ſleeps the ſleep of death, he doth not feel, nor is he ſenſible of any of the calamities or ſad provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of God upon the Earth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seventhly,</hi> When a man goeth to ſleep, he goeth to ſleep but for a certain time; in the morning he awakes out of his ſleep: So it is with the ſleep of death; and therefore death is called a ſleep, becauſe we muſt all awake in the morning of Reſurrection. We are in the Grave as in our Beds, and when the Trumpet of God, and the voice of the Arch-Angel ſhall ſound, we ſhall all ariſe out of our Graves as out of our Beds: Death is but a ſleep for a certain time.</p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:150340:61"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eighthly,</hi> Sleep is a great refreſhing to thoſe that are weary, and ſick; and when the ſick man awakes, he is more lively and chearful than he was before he fell aſleep; and therefore ſleep is called, <hi>Medicus laborum redintegratio vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium, recreator corporum,</hi> the great Phyſician of the ſick Body, the renewing of man's Spirits, the reviver of the weary Body. And ſo it is with death: When God's People awake out of the ſleep of death, they ſhall be more active for God than ever they were before. When you lie down in the Grave, you ſhall lie down with mortal Bodies, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42, 43. <hi>It is ſown a mortal body, but it ſhall riſe up an immortal body; it is ſown in diſhonour, but it ſhall riſe up in honour; it is ſown a natural body, but it ſhall riſe up a ſpiritual body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nithly,</hi> As in the morning when we riſe out of our Beds, we then put on our cloaths, ſo in the morning of the glorious Reſurrection, we ſhall put on a glorious Body, like to the glorious Body of Jeſus Chriſt: We ſhall put on <hi>Stolam Immortalitatis,</hi> the Garment of Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tenthly,</hi> As no man when he lieth down to ſleep, knoweth the direct time when he ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, ſo no man can tell when the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall be. They do but cozen you, who ſay, That the general Reſurrection ſhall be ſuch or ſuch a year: For as no man can know the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:150340:61"/>when he ſhall awake out of his natural ſleep, no more can any man know when we ſhall arife from the ſleep of death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eleventhly,</hi> As it is a very eaſie thing to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake a man out of ſleep, it is but ſtirring of him, and you will awake him quickly; ſo it is with the ſleep of death: It is as eaſie for Jeſus Chriſt to awake us out of the ſleep of death, as it is for you or me to awake a man out of his ſleep in Bed: <hi>Nemo noſtrum tam facile excitat dormientem de lecto, quam Chriſtus jacentem in Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchro.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Twelfthly,</hi> As when a man riſeth in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, tho he hath ſlept many hours; nay, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he could ſleep twenty years together, yet notwithſtanding when he awakes, theſe twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years will ſeem to be but as one hour unto him: So it will be in the day of Judgment, all thoſe that are in their Graves, when they awake, it will be <hi>tanquam ſomnus unius horae,</hi> as the ſleep of one hour unto them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Laſtly,</hi> And moſt eſpecially, as ſleep ſeizeth only upon the Body, and the outward Senſes, but doth not ſeize upon the Soul. The Soul of man is oftentimes moſt buſie when the man is aſleep.</p>
                  <p>And God hath heretofore revealed moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things to his children in dreams, when they have been aſleep: God appeared unto <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> and many others, in dreams. The Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:150340:62"/>ſleeps, but the Soul awakes. So it is with the ſleep of death; it is the Body that dies, but the Soul doth not die. There are ſome men that are not afraid to teach you, that the Soul ſleeps as well as the Body; and that when the Body dies, and falls aſleep, the Soul likewiſe continues in a dull Lethargy: <hi>Veternoſo ſomno correptus:</hi> neither capable of joy nor ſorrow till the Reſurrection.</p>
                  <p>Beloved, this is very uncomfortable, and a very falſe Doctrine. They endeavour to prove it from my Text: They ſay, That when <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> died, he fell aſleep. It is true, in regard of his Body, he fell aſleep, but his Soul did not fall aſleep: That which was ſtoned fell aſleep, which was his Body only; for when he was ſtoning, he ſaw Jeſus Chriſt ſtanding ready to receive his Soul into Heaven: <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive my ſpirit. Stephen</hi>'s Soul could not be ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, tho his Body was ſtoned. So when Jeſus Chriſt was crucified, his Soul was not crucified, I mean, when his Body was killed. Indeed he did endure torments in his Soul, which made him cry out, <hi>My God, my God, why hast thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me?</hi> But yet his Soul did not die. So when <hi>Stephen</hi> died, his Soul went to Chriſt. It is true, when a child of God dies, the Soul goes to ſleep. How is that? The Soul goes to ſleep in a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſenſe; that is, it goes to reſt in <hi>Ahraham</hi>'s Boſome. O bleſſed Sleep! it goes to reſt in the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:150340:62"/>Embraces of God; it goes into the Arms of its Redeemer; it goes to the Heavenly Paradice; it goes to be always preſent with the Lord. But take heed you do not ſay, that the Soul ſleeps in this ſenſe; <hi>viz.</hi> That it lies in a ſtrange kind of a Lethargy, neither dead nor alive, neither capable of joy nor ſorrow until the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Tho <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Body fell aſleep, yet his Soul did not fall aſleep, but immediately went unto Jeſus Chriſt in Heaven. Thus I have given the Explication of the Words.</p>
                  <p>Now give me leave to make ſome Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all unto our ſelves.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. If the death of God's children be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a falling aſleep, then let this comfort us againſt the death of our godly Friends, tho they die unnatural and violent deaths, tho they be ſtoned to death, tho they be burnt to aſhes, tho they be ſawn aſunder. Here is a meſſage of rich conſolation, which as a Miniſter of Chriſt, I hold unto you this day; <hi>viz.</hi> That the death of a child of God, let it be after what manner ſoever it will, it is nothing but a falling aſleep; He goes to his Grave as to his Bed: And therefore our Burying-places are call'd our <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitoria,</hi> Sleeping-houſes. A child of God when he dies, he lies down in peace, and enters into his reſt: And as a man, when he is aſleep, is free from all the cares and troubles that he hath in
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:150340:63"/>the day-time, ſo the People of God, when they are fallen aſleep, they are free from all the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and calamities, croſſes, loſſes and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that we are troubled withal: Therefore give me leave to ſay to you, as Chriſt did to the Women that followed him to the Croſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing and lamenting of him: <hi>O daughters of Jeruſalem, weep not for me, but weep for your ſelves, and for your children:</hi> So I ſay, weep not for thoſe that are dead in the Lord, that are fallen aſleep in Jeſus Chriſt: They are at their reſts; they do not know the troubles that we are troubled withal: <hi>Abraham</hi> remembers us not: they are not ſenſible of our miſeries and afflictions. Let us weep for our ſelves, and for the miſeries that are coming upon us; and let us know, that when God's children die, they do but lie in their Beds until the morning of the Reſurrection, and then they ſhall put on <hi>Stolam Immortalitatis,</hi> the Garment of Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, and their Bodies ſhall be made like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the glorious Body of Jeſus Chriſt. And know one thing more, which is all in all, <hi>viz.</hi> That when the Body of a child of God falls aſleep, his Soul immediately goes into the Arms of Chriſt, and there lives for ever in the Embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Jeſus Chriſt: Tho the Body falls aſleep, yet the Soul is received into <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Boſom. I beſeech you comfort one another with theſe words.</p>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:150340:63"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. Let me beſeech the people of God, that they would look upon death, not as it is preſented unto us in Natures Looking-glaſs, but as it is ſet down in a Scripture-dreſs. Nature preſents death in a very terrible manner: and it is true, death is very terrible to a man out of Chriſt; but to you that are in Chriſt, the ſting of death is taken away: Death is nothing elſe but a quiet and placid Sleep, putting off our cloaths and going to Bed, till we awake in the morning of Reſurrection. Death to a child of God is nothing but a putting off his Earthly Tabernacle, a going from an Earthly Priſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Heavenly Palace, a hoiſing up Sail for Heaven, the letting of the Soul out of Priſon, as a Bird out of a Cage, that it may fly to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; a change from a Temporary Hell to an Eternal Heaven, a going out of <hi>Egypt</hi> into <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan:</hi> and therefore called, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15. not <hi>mors hominis,</hi> but <hi>mors peccati,</hi> not the death of the man, but the death of his ſins; it is <hi>Sepultura vitiorum;</hi> it is the Pilgrim's Journeys end, the Seaman's Haven, an abſence from the Body, and a preſence with the Lord. Let all God's People look upon death through Scripture-Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles, and conſider it as it is ſweetly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in this Text. Remember bleſſed <hi>Stephen</hi> ſtoned to death, and yet falling aſleep; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member alſo that Excellent Saying of St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> That a child of God ſhould be as willing
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:150340:64"/>to die as to put off his cloaths, becauſe death is nothing elſe to him but a Sleep, and a departure from miſery to everlaſting happineſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Uſe</hi> 3. Is to beſeech you all every night when you go to Bed, to remember this Text, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially theſe Four things: Firſt, When you are putting off your cloaths, remember you muſt ſhortly put off your Bodies. And Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, When you go into your Beds, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that it will not be long before you go into your Graves. And Thirdly, When you cloſe your Eyes to ſleep, remember that it will not be long before death muſt cloſe your Eyes. And Fourthly, When you awake in the morning, remember that at the Reſurrection we muſt all ariſe out of the Grave; and that the juſt ſhall ariſe to everlaſting happineſs, but the wicked to everlaſting miſery.</p>
                  <p>It is the ſaying on a Heathen man, That the whole Life of a man ſhould be nothing elſe but <hi>Meditatio Mortis,</hi> a Meditation of Death: And it is the ſaying of <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 32.29. <hi>O that men were wiſe, that they underſtood this, that they would conſider their latter end.</hi> Beloved, it is the greateſt part of Wiſdom every day to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our latter end: That man is the only wiſe man, and happy man in life and death, that is ever mindful of his end.</p>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:150340:64"/>
                  <p>But before I make an end, I muſt propound one Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> whether the death of the wicked be not in Scripture compared to a Sleep as well as the death of the godly? I anſwer, That wicked men in Scripture are ſaid to fall aſleep when they die: It is ſaid of Idolatrous <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> that <hi>he ſlept with his fathers:</hi> of <hi>Baa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha</hi> and <hi>Omri,</hi> thoſe wicked Kings, that <hi>they ſlept with their fathers.</hi> But then the Queſtion will be, In what reſpect is the death of the wicked compared to a Sleep? <hi>Anſ.</hi> Even as a man which is aſleep, ſometimes hath no bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, reſt, or eaſe thereby; when the ſick man awakes, he is many times more ſick than he was before he went to ſleep. Some men are much diſquieted in their ſleeps by hideous and fearful dreams: <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> when he was aſleep, had a moſt ſcaring dream, and was ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed therewith. So it is with a wicked man; death to a wicked man is a Sleep, but it is a terrifying Sleep: The Soul, that goes immediately to Hell, where it is burned with fire that never ſhall be quenched, and where the Worm that never dies, is always gnawing upon it; The Body, that indeed lies aſleep in the Grave: But how? Even as a Malefactor that ſleeps in a Priſon the night before he is to be executed, but when he awakes, is hurried and dragged to Execution: So the wicked man falls aſleep in death, but when he awakes, he awakes to everlaſting dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation;
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:150340:65"/>but a child of God when he ſleeps the Sleep of death, he ſleeps in his Father's Houſe, and when he awakes, he awakes to everlaſting happineſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Uſe</hi> 4. And this makes way for the Fourth and laſt Uſe, which Uſe is of very great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, and that is, to beſeech all, that you labour ſo to live, that when you fall aſleep you may ſleep an happy Sleep. There is the Sleep that the wicked man ſleeps when he dies, and there is the Sleep that the godly man ſleeps when he dies: Now I beſeech you labour ſo to live, that when you fall aſleep, your Sleep may be an happy Sleep unto you, that when you awake in the morning of the Reſurrection, it may be a good awaking for you.</p>
                  <p>But then the great Queſtion will be, How ſhall I do this?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſhall give you Four or Five helps for this:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> If you would ſleep an happy Sleep at death, then you muſt labour to ſleep in Jeſus Chriſt. It is ſaid, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.18. <hi>Then they alſo which are fallen aſleep in Chriſt.</hi> And 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14. <hi>If we believe that Jeſus died, and roſe again, even ſo them alſo which ſleep in Jeſus will God bring with him.</hi> What is it to ſleep in Jeſus? To ſleep in Jeſus is to die in the Faith of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:150340:65"/>
                  <p n="2">2. To ſleep in Jeſus Chriſt, is to die with an Intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt, to die as a Member u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited to Chriſt, as our Head: For you muſt know, that the duſt of a Saint is part of that man who is a Member of Jeſus Chriſt; and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry believer, when he ſleeps in the duſt, he ſleeps in Jeſus Chriſt; that is, he lies in the Grave, and his duſt is part of Chriſt Myſtical; and Chriſt as an Head, will raiſe it up, and cannot be compleat without it. Now then if ever you would ſleep an happy Sleep, labour to get a real Intereſt in Chriſt: labour to live in Chriſt while you live, and then when you fall aſleep, you ſhall be ſure to ſleep in Jeſus. There are many that would have Chriſt to receive their Souls at death, and that ſay with dying <hi>Stephen, Lord Jeſus receive my ſpirit:</hi> But if ever you would have Chriſt to receive your Souls when you die, you muſt be ſure to receive him into your Souls whilſt you live: If ever you would have him to receive you into Heaven, you muſt receive him into your hearts. No man makes a Will, but he ſaith, <hi>Imprimis,</hi> I bequeath my Soul to Jeſus Chriſt, my Redeemer. But how doſt thou know that Jeſus Chriſt will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of this Legacy? If thy Soul hath not Chriſt's Image upon it, if it be not regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and renewed, Jeſus Chriſt will never own it: Thou maiſt bequeath it unto Chriſt, but the Devil will claim it. Beloved, if ever you
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:150340:66"/>would reign with Chriſt when you die, he muſt reign in you whilſt you live; and if ever you would ſleep an happy Sleep, you muſt live in Jeſus, that you may ſleep in Jeſus.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In the Third place, if ever you would ſleep an happy Sleep at death, then you muſt take heed of overcharging your ſelf with world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cares. A man that is full of cares cannot ſleep: They lay (as the Proverb is) all their cares under their Pillow: they labour to ſhut all cares out of their mind. O take heed that you do not murder your ſelves by the cares of the World. Beloved, a man that eats out his heart with Worldly Cares, will never ſleep an happy Sleep, the Cares of the World will choak all the good Seed of the Word of God: And therefore as men, when they go to ſleep, lay aſide all Worldly Thoughts, ſo if ever you will ſleep an happy Sleep, take heed of overmuch carking and caring for the things of this World: And remember what you have heard this day, and that will regulate and moderate all your cares. Naked you came into the World, and naked you muſt go out of the World. Why ſhould we take care for that we know not who ſhall enjoy after us.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. If ever you would ſleep an happy Sleep when you die, you muſt take heed of ſucking too much of the pleaſures of this World. A man that eats a full ſupper, will ſleep very diſquietly:
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:150340:66"/>Therefore they that would ſleep quietly, uſe to eat light ſuppers: For when a man's ſtomach is over-charged, it takes away his quiet Sleep from him. So if you would ſleep an happy Sleep when you come to die, O take heed of ſucking too much the Pleaſures of this Life: take heed of eating too large a Meal of World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Delights, and of Creature-Comforts. Theſe Worldly Pleaſures will make the Sleep of Death unquiet unto you. O! let not <hi>Dalilah</hi>'s lap de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive you of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s boſome: Remember, that <hi>David,</hi> by <hi>Bathſheba</hi>'s Embraces, loſt the Embraces of God: I mean the ſence of the Embraces of God, the joy and comfort of them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> If ever you would ſleep an happy Sleep in death, then labour to work hard for Heaven while you live. O how delightful is Sleep to a weary man: When a man hath taken pains all the day, as the Traveller that hath travelled all the day, or the Plowman that hath been at work all the day, how quietly, how ſoundly doth he ſleep in the night! O beloved, if ever you would ſleep an happy Sleep at death, then <hi>work out your ſalvation with fear and trembling,</hi> and give all diligence to make your <hi>calling and election ſure.</hi> The more you labour for Heaven, the better, the ſweeter will your ſleep be when you come to die. And remember this, as much ſleeping in the day-time will hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a man's Sleep at night, ſo you that idle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:150340:67"/>way the time of your providing for Heaven in this your day, you that ſleep away the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute on which Eternity doth depend, O! you will have a ſad Sleep when death ſeizeth upon you. Take heed therefore of ſleeping whilſt you live, that ſo your ſleep in the night of death may be comfortable unto you.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. And laſtly, If ever you would ſleep an happy ſleep when you die, then take heed of the ſleep of ſin. Sin in the Scripture is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a ſleep: <hi>Awake thou that ſleepeſt:</hi> that is, thou that ſinneſt. Sin is ſuch a ſleep as brings the ſleep of death: Sin brings the firſt death, and ſin brings the ſecond death: All miſeries whatſoever are the daughters of ſin. If you would ſleep an happy ſleep, and have an happy awakening at the Reſurrection, then take heed of the ſleep of ſin: <hi>Awake thou that ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, ariſe from the dead, and Jeſus Chriſt will give thee life, Eph.</hi> 5.14. ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.11, 12, 13. with which I will conclude; and I pray you, mark it well: for it was a Text that converted St. <hi>Auguſtine: Knowing the time, beloved, that it is now high time to awake out of ſleep: for now is our ſalvation nearer than when we believed. The night is far ſpent, the day is at hand: Let us therefore caſt off the works of darkneſs, and let us put on the armour of light: let us walk honeſtly, as in the day, not in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oting and drunkenneſs, not in chambering and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs, not in ſtrife and envying;</hi> but put on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:150340:67"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Books Printed for</hi> Richard Butler, <hi>in</hi> White-Lyon-Court <hi>in</hi> Barbican.</head>
                  <p>A Practical and ſhort Expoſition of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by way of Queſtion and Anſwer: Wherein the Divine Authority and Reaſonableneſs of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Queſtion and Anſwer, every Doctrine and Practice in it recommended, are Evidenced and Improved againſt moſt Contemners of it, and Diſſenters from it; with that Moderation and Plainneſs, that it may engage all to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to, and eſpecially may inſtruct Children in the true Proteſtant Religion of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Humbly offered for the good of Schools and Youth. By <hi>Nathanael Taylor,</hi> M. A.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: Or the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of Infants Vindicated by Scriptures and Reaſons. Humbly offered in Order to a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure of Differences at this Juncture of Time. By <hi>Nath. Taylor,</hi> M. A.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: Or an Alphebetical Martyrology, containing the Trials and Dying Expreſſions of many Martyrs of Note ſince Chriſt. Extracted out of <hi>Foxe</hi>'s Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:150340:68"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:150340:68"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:150340:69"/>numents of the Church. With an Alphabetical Liſt of God's Judgments remarkably ſhown on many Noted and Cruel Perſecutors. Together with an Appendix of things pertinent to the underſtanding this Martyrology. By <hi>N. T.</hi> M. A. T. C. C.</p>
                  <p>Two Sermons of Hypocriſie, and the vain hope of ſelf-deceiving ſinners: Together with an Inſpection into the Manners and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> whoſe fruits betel them to be Men of a Worldly Spirit, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting true holineſs, and ſtrangers to the ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that is in Chriſt: All which is ſhewed in the following Treatiſe, compoſed and publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the common good, the ſtartling and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakening of all Worldly and Opinionative Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, of what Name or Sect ſoever, and particularly the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and the eſtabliſhment and conſolation of the upright and ſound in heart, in perilous and ſhaking times, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for a further confutation of <hi>Quakeriſm.</hi> By <hi>John Cheyney.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150340:69"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150340:70"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150340:70"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
